<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands pvrginge fire Conteyninge two petitions, the one to the Kinges most excellent Majesty, the other to the High Courte of Parliament held at this tyme in England. Shewinge in diverse perticulers, how the Church in England might be ordered, yet more conformably to the Will of God reveiled in his worde then at this day it is. Herewithall is declared, the evell and lamentable effects of our vnable and negligent ministers: and the happy fruict of our learned and painefull pastors. A worke most needefull for theise tymes, as servinge to turne away the wrath and iudgements of God from this lande, through the removinge, (accordinge to the advertisements herein given) such disorders and evells, as for which the wrath of God may be, and is, kindled against this Land, and the church therein.</title>
            <author>Proctor, Thomas, fl. 1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20408.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900293</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900293</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150735</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150735)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1976:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands pvrginge fire Conteyninge two petitions, the one to the Kinges most excellent Majesty, the other to the High Courte of Parliament held at this tyme in England. Shewinge in diverse perticulers, how the Church in England might be ordered, yet more conformably to the Will of God reveiled in his worde then at this day it is. Herewithall is declared, the evell and lamentable effects of our vnable and negligent ministers: and the happy fruict of our learned and painefull pastors. A worke most needefull for theise tymes, as servinge to turne away the wrath and iudgements of God from this lande, through the removinge, (accordinge to the advertisements herein given) such disorders and evells, as for which the wrath of God may be, and is, kindled against this Land, and the church therein.</title>
                  <author>Proctor, Thomas, fl. 1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>86, [2] p. ,   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>G. Veseler],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Thomas Proctor.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 5: To the Kings Most Excellent Maiesty·</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150735:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150735:1"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS PVRGINGE FIRE.</p>
            <p>Conteyninge two Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the one to the Kinges moſt excellent Majeſty, the other to the High Courte of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament held at this tyme in England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewinge in diverſe perticulers, how the Church in England might be ordered, yet more conſormably to the will of God reveiled in his Worde, then at this day it is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herewithall is declared, the evell and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table effects of our vnable and negligent Miniſters: and the happy fruict of our learned and painefull Paſtors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A worke most needefull for theiſe tymes, as ſervinge to turne away the wrath and Iudgements of God from this Lande, through the removinge, (accordinge to the Advertiſements herein given) ſuch diſorders and evells, as for which the wrath of God may be, and is, kindled againſt this Land, and the Church therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IER. 6, 16.</bibl> Thus faith the Lord, ſtand in the wayes, and behold, and aſke of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient paths, which is the good way, and walke therein, and ye ſhall finde reſt for your Soules.</q>
            <p>16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150735:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150735:2"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS PVRGINGE FIRE.</head>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>To the Right Honorable, the Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and Temporall of the upper Hovvſe, vvith the Knights and Burgeſſes of the lovver hovvſe, aſſembled in the high Courte of Parliament.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſed the Kinges moſt excellent Maſtie, very lately to confeſs among you, that in the Civill affaires off this Kingdome, he founde not things anſwerable to that face, which our excellent Government would induce any man to have hope of; Might it therefore pleaſe this Honorable Aſsembly, to examine the State of this Lande, in Spirituall affaires alſo, we then the ſubjects of this happy Kingedome may well have comforteable hope, of your happy ſucceſse in theiſe as in thoſe. It is truly a greate meaſure of Happineſs to this Kingdome: it is alſo to be acknowledged to our Kinge as a ſingular Grace off his unto us, that the Ghoſpell of our Lord &amp; Redeemer is freely preached in this Kingdome, Solemne Divine Service maintayned, and people preſſed to reſorte on the Sabbaoth to both; but becauſe the prevailinge of the Ghoſpell, in the lives and converſations of men is moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God: and becauſe our people are not anſwereable herein to the face of that excellent Government which our Church carryes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150735:3"/>I moſt humbly pray that I may petition this Courte, for an entringe into an examination hereof alſo. For my part, I havinge here in this Land drawen my firſt breath of this mortall life, thinke my ſelfe bounde, to imploy whatſoeuer Grace my God hath given mee for the Good thereof; therefore I have adventured to expoſe my ſelfe to danger, in movinge you to vouchſafe your examination, of the State alſo of the Church in this Kingedome. This high, (and worthily Highe) Courte, hath here to fore taken care, that God be both ſolemnely worſhipped, and alſo ſerved in this Land by peoples obedience, acknowledginge that this is the Meanes to put away pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments and plagues from this Lande: As therefore the Ghoſpell is not ſent by God to be hearde onely by our people, but to be obeyed alſo, by their ordering their life and converſation thereafter, or otherwiſe ſerves vnto condemnation, rather then to Salvation, ſo ſurely it will turne from us puniſhments and plagues, and inſteade of them will bringe vpon us holy favours and Bleſsings, if you take care of the peoples livinge as becommeth Saincts. For the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theringe whereof, I by a writinge adventured many yeares ſince to petition his ſacred Majeſtie, declaringe therein the perticulers wherein I petitioned his Roy all Aſsiſtance: If it ſhall pleaſe you (Right Honorable) that I, for diſcharge of my Conſcience, may exhibit vnto you the copie (well neere) of the ſame, that ſo both his ſacred Majestie may be put in remembrance thereof, in this ſo ſit a tyme for this motion: and alſo you may bee occaſioned, as you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly tender, ſo now alſo to further, the good of this Church, you ſhall ſhew to me a Christian favour, and I ſhall pray for you, that God will ſecond with happy ſuccrſs all your pious indeavours.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Lo<hi rend="sup">pps</hi> in all bounden Duty. <hi>THOMAS PROCTOR.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150735:3"/>
               <head>TO THE KINGES <hi>MOST EXCELLENT</hi> MAIESTY.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O my heartes ioye, and to the ioye of all good Chriſtians, have you (my moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Lord and Kinge) made knovven to the vvorlde by vvritinge, your knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the office of a Chriſtian Kinge. As vvhere you vvrite, That Chriſtian Kinges within their owne Dominions, are, to Governe the Church, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande obedience to be given to the vvorde of God, yea and to Reforme Religion, according to Gods preſcribed vvill. Which Office, (moſt mighty, and dread Soveraigne) vvell may you perfourme: longe may you live, vvell to perfourme the ſame, vvithin theiſe your moſt flouriſhinge Kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. Imitatinge herein the good Kinges of Iſraell and Iudah, vvhom and vvhoſe Actions in Governinge the Church, your Majeſtly hath ſet before Chriſtian Kinges and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150735:4"/>Princes as examples unto them, for their rulinge over the Chriſtian Church, vvithin their ſeuerall Dominions. Which excellent knovvledge and religious Care of your Majeſties ſo made euident to the vvorlde, put me in good hope that it vvould not be diſpleaſinge vnto you, if collectinge out of Scripture ſome of the ſpeciall Acts of thoſe good Kinges of Iſraell and Iudah, I thereby tooke occaſion to vvrite vnto your Majeſty of ſome thinges of greate importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vvherein the Church of God in England needeth the redreſs of your povverfull hande. Which thinge (Dread Soueraigne) I have not done, either vvith any vaine conceipt, thinking to better by inſtruction your excellent knovvledge: or vvith any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable preſumption, in preſſinge your executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Royall Dutyes vvith more haſt then convenience; but onely, that I might diſcharge a Chriſtian Duty, by petitioninge your povverfull Aſſiſtance in ſome things, vvherein your tymely helpe may greately further the good of the Church of God. Neither truly is there any thinge better beſittinge your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hande, then is the yeildinge ſuccour to the Church of God, in thoſe things vvherein ſhee greately needeth in theiſe tymes your aide; For, thus to doe, is not onely the perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of a very ſpeciall duty of the kingely office, but alſo, it is an eterniznge of your fame, in the eternal continuance of the Church. Hovv pretious a Name, hovv longe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe a Fame, have thoſe good Kinges of Iſraell and Iudah obteined, by vvhoſe bleſſed hands tymely aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vvas yeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Church of God? VVhat marble Monument of theirs like this? VVhat other Act of theirs is comparable to this? Their marble monuments are mouldred: and their other Acts hovv greate and famous ſo euer, yet make they not their Name and Memoriall ſo bleſſed, as doth the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde of thoſe things done by them, in ordeninge the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Gouerment according to Gods preſcribed vvill. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150735:4"/>therefore, both of your Majeſties beinge like mynded vvith theſe good Kings, and alſo of your gratious acceptance of this my poore vvritinge, vvritten for the good of this Church of Englande, I humbly pray, that I may prooceede, firſt, to collect out of the Scriptures ſome of the ſpeciall Acts of the good Kinges of Iſraell and Iudah concerninge this matter of orderinge the Church: and ſecondly, (takinge oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion therefrom) to ſhevv, vvherein, or in vvhat needefull perticulers, I, (in all humility) crave your Royal Povverfull Aſſiſtance.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>I. CHAP.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OF David we reade, 1. Chron, 24, 3: That he distributed Zadock of the ſonnes of Eleazar, and Ahimilech of the ſonnes of Ithamar, accordinge to their Offices in their Ministration. Againe; Of Hezekiah we reade, 2. Chron, 31, 2: That he appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the courſes of the Preiſts and Levits, by their turnes, euery man accordinge to his office, both Preiſts and Leuits, for the burnts Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and peace Offerings, to Miniſter, and to give thancks, &amp; to praiſe, in the gates of the tents of the Lord. Againe, we reade of the ſame Kinge, 2. Chron, 24, 25: That he appointed alſo the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits in the houſe of the Lord, with Cymbals, with Viols, and with Harps, accordinge to the commandement of David, and Gad the Kinges Secr, and Nathan the Prophet: for the commandement (noteth this Scripture) was by the Hande of the Lord, and by the hande of his Prophets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence vve have evidence, that the Kinges Office ſtreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, to order the Eccleſiaſtical Miniſters &amp; Miniſtrations, accordinge to the Ordinance or Commandement of God;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150735:5"/>therefore Kinges are Gods Miniſters, to ſee that ſuch Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Officers &amp; Offices as God ordeyned in the Church, be founde in the Church of God vvithin their ſeuerall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. But hovv cann Kinges vnder the Chriſtianity doe this, if they have not povver over thoſe, in vvhom is the povver of Ordeyninge Eccleſiaſtical Miniſters, conſtreyninge them (if neede be) to ordeine ſuch Miniſters as neede? For Miniſters muſt firſt be, before they can be diſtributed to the ſeuerall Offices; neither can our Kinges diſtribute Miniſters to the ſeuerall Offices, if they have not power over thoſe by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiaſtical Ordination is conveyed. Vnder the Lawe, Miniſters vvere propagated by Generatiö; vnder the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel they are propagated by Ordination; therefore vvhere Miniſters vvant to be diſtributed to due Offices, the Kinge is Gods Miniſter to conſtreine (if neede be) the Miniſter vvho hath povver of Ordination, to ordeine Miniſters for needefull offices. Such eccleſiaſticall Miniſters therefore, as God by his vvoorde preſerved in Scripture, giues us light &amp; vvarrant for that they ought to be in the Church, vve may petition your Majeſtie that they be ordeined and diſtributed to their appointed Offices, if our Cleargy in vvhom is the povver of Ordination be herein negligent. True it is, that this Church hath bene very happy, in its preſervinge in the Reformation, Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacons: and vve of theiſe tymes are herein likevviſe happy, that ſuch are continued in this Church vvith your Majeſties gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious allovvance; therefore I am not in this Chapter to petition for the ordeyninge of ſuch Miniſters. That vvhich I petition your Majeſtie for in this Chapter is:
<list>
                        <item>1. That ſuch eccleſiaſticall Officers as are wantinge in our Church, may be ordeyned in this Church.</item>
                        <item>2. That Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iſhes, Biſhopdomes, and Arch Biſhopdomes, may be conveniently bounded.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150735:5"/>3. That you continue to free this Church, from all forreine and unlaw full eccleſiaſticall uſurpations &amp; Powers.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>THoſe eccleſiaſticall Officers which I accoumpt to wante unto our Church, are, Lay Elders or Governours in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Parriſh Church, who, with, though under the Cleargy in that Church, ſhould Governe the Church in that Parriſh. But becauſe theiſe are not onely not as yet admitted in this Church, but alſo are by our Cleargy comtemptuouſly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of, and ſpoaken againſt, therefore I humbly pray, that I may, firſt, ſhew by the vvord of God in Scripture, that God Orderned ſuch in the Church: and ſecondly, that I may anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were ſome queſtions which may be moved concerning ſuch.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle S. Paule, 1. Cor. 12, 28, ſaith thus: And God hath ordeined ſome in the Church, as firſt Apoſtles, ſecondly Prophets, thirdly Teachers, then them that doe Miracles: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, the guifts of healinge, Helpers, Governours, diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of tongues. From vvhich Scripture appeares, that by Gods Ordinance there vvere in thoſe time Governours in the Church, which both were inferior to Teachers, and alſo were not Teachers. That they were to be inferior to Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers appeares, in that they are ranked in order farr under Teachers: for as Teachers here rancked under Apoſtles in Order, were doubtleſs inferior to Apoſtles, ſo theiſe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours thus rancked under Teachers in Order, were inferior to Teachers. And that they were not Teachers may appeare, in that, verſe, 29, the Apoſtle ſaith: Are all Apoſtles? are all Prophets? are all Teachers? for this manner interrogation of the Apoſtles proves, that as all Teachers were not Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſo thoſe named after Teachers were not Teachers. And indeede why ſaith the Apoſtle, are all Teachers? if it miply not, that thoſe which follow Teachers were not to be Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150735:6"/>I conclude therefore from this Scripture, that it was Gods owne Ordinance, that there ſhould be in the Church a ſorte of Governours beſides Teachers, and which might not be Teachers.</p>
                  <p>To this wee may add yet a further evidence for this, which we have by another portion of Scripture, as, 1. Tim. 5, 17, where we thus reade: The Elders that Rule well, are worthie of double Honour: ſpecially they that labour in the vvorde and Doctrine. Where, the Apoſtle not proceedinge from Teachinge to labouringe in Teachinge, but from Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge to labouringe in the vvorde, this argues undeniably, that ſome for Rulinge vvell onely, were worthy of double Honor, For when the Apoſtle ſaith, The Elders that Rule well are vvorthie of double Honour, who cann deny double honor to theiſe if they onely Ruled vvell, and Taught not at all? Therefore I cannot but conclude, that in thoſe times there vvere Governours in the Church, who for Rulinge well onely, though they laboured not in the vvorde, were worthy of double Honor. And indeede if here we ſhould take the conſtruction which ſome make of this ſpeach, wher they ſay, that here the Apoſtle meanes that all theiſe Elders are Teachers, and that he ſpecially commends ſome of them for labouringe, or taking more paines in the vvorde then others tooke then it would followe firſt, that not for Ruling well onely ſome were to have double Honor, (which thing is directly againſt this Scripture): ſecondly that ſome Teachers were worthy of double honor for Rulinge well onely, though they Taught not at all; but this were an error not to be conceaved in the Apoſtle, ſeing not to Teach but onely Rule, is in a Teacher or Preacher of the Ghoſpell, ſuch a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of a very ſpeciall Duty, as that ſuch Teacher is worthy rather of Reproofe and Puniſhment then of double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. Moreover, if the Apoſtle would have us underſtande,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150735:6"/>that ſome Teachers are worthy of double Honor for Rulinge well, but ſpecially ſuch as labour more painefully in Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge, then it had benefit he ſhould have ſaid: Thoſe El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that teach and Rule well, are worthy of double Honor: ſpecially they that labour in the vvord more then others: for verily, it is an unfit ſkippinge from Rulinge, to a degree of Compariſon in Teachinge Laſtly, ſeing Preachinge is a labour, the Apoſtle might well ſay, ſpecially they that labour and yet without making uſe of any compariſon betweene them and other Teachers; neither indeede cann it be ſaid, that any one that Teacheth at all, laboureth not in the worde and Doctryne. Theiſe things conſidered, we have good warrant from this Scripture to collect and affirme: That in aſmuch as none may deny but that by this ſpeach, ſome were to have double Honour though they Ruled well onely: And in aſmuch as no Teacher but deſervs reproofe if he Rule well onely and Teach not; Therefore here is an evidence, That the Chriſtian Church was to have in it Elders, who were not to be Teachers but Rulers onely. This evidence from ſacred Scripture for ſuch Governours conſidered, how cann any ſafely oppoſe the worke of one of the ſpeciall Angells of the Reformation, even Calvin, in his reſtoringe ſuch to the Church of God? Doubtleſs a ſpeciall Act of a ſpeciall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Reformation, is no ſmale bond unto the reſt of the Churches Reformed, ſpecially when it hath this Light from Scripture, of the correſpondence thereof to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, in the firſt and Apoſtolically planted Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Thus having proved, that Governours who were not Teachers, were yet ordeined by God to be in the Church, I now pray that I may proceede, to anſwer certaine queſtions, which may by ſome be moved co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch Governours.</p>
                  <p>Some may ſay: If theiſe were then in the Church, yet, is there any neceſſity that ſuch ſhould be now alſo in our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150735:7"/>Church? I anſwere, Though all Officers and Offices which we fynde by Scripture to have bene in the Church, be not neceſſarily to be now alſo in our tymes in the Church, (for vve read of Apoſtles, Prophets to foretell things, alſo of vvorkers of Miracles, Speakers of Tongues, Interpreters of Tongues, &amp;c: all which being by extraordinary Guifts of the Spirit, the Guift failinge, the Office and Officer faileth alſo) yet, ſuch Offices as might be executed vvithout ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Gifts, vvere to be continued in the Church. And indeede vvhy have vve Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacons, if not becauſe ſuch were ordeyned in the firſt plantation of the Church, and might be continued by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination vvithout any Neede of any extraordinary Guifts of the Spirit? As therefore vve are neceſſarily to follow the example of Gods Ordinance in the beginning for theiſe, ſo the ſame example is a bond, for the Churches havinge in it alſo ſuch Governours as now I vvrite of. To conclude, as in the Reformation we retayne ſuch Cleargy and Offices, as which have ſome evidence in holy Scripture to be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Gods Ordinance in the Church in the firſt tymes, ſo this evidence in Scripture for Governours who are not to be Teachers, ought to be a bond to the Church, to reſtore this Ordinance of God to the Church in the Reformation made. For ſeinge vve followe not Tradition vvithout ſome evidence in Scripture for other Offices of our Cleargy, vve ought not to followe the corruption and neglect of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, againſt the Scriptures light yeilded us for ſuch Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours as now I vvrite. Let us not therefore kick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Ordinance: Let us not deſpiſe it as a neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thinge: Let us not bringe downe viſitations upon us for ſuch neglect: Let us not ſay all is already vvell Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, vvhen yet ſuch Governours are not in our Church; but rather let us meekely beare the yoake of this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150735:7"/>Ordinance of God alſo, that ſo our people and Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may hereby be the more Chriſtianly Governed. Cann vve thinke that the Neglect of ſuch an Ordinance of God, vvill not breede a defect in the vvell Governinge of the Church? Doubtleſs, as all the Ordinances of God rended to the furtherance of the Ghoſpells out ſpreadinge, and well Governinge them converted by the Ghoſpell, ſo where ſo ſpeaciall an Ordinance is omitted, as is this of plantinge Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours vvho are not Teachers, there, both the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell vvill the leſs prevaile, and the people alſo vvill be the more negligent, to bringe fourth the fruicts thereof in their life and converſation. Doe but looke upon the difference of people, and effect of the Ghoſpell, vvhere ſuch Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours are, and vvhere they are not reſtored, and by the evidence vvhich experience yeilds, be moved to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Benefit of reſtoringe this Ordinance of the Lords.</p>
                  <p>Againe ſome may ſay: <hi>How have theiſe failed all this tyme?</hi> To this alſo I anſwere, It is indeede uncertaine hovv; but yet, ſeinge vve fynde by the vvorde of God that by Gods Ordinance ſuch vvere planted in the Church, vve have good cauſe to Beleeve, that by ſome corruption of Tradition they failed. For my parte, I conceave, That ſoone after the Apoſtles tymes, the Church converted all Church Officers into Cleargy, and by makinge all Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, the uſe of Lay Governours falled. Moreover, the convertinge them into Cleargy, might occaſion that they were not founde in after tyme in every Church, becauſe of the inſupportable burthen of every Church or Congregations maintayninge of its Charge many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
                  <p>Againe ſome may ſay: <hi>Are they then to be Lay Men?</hi> I anſwere, yes; for if God exempt not any as for his Cleargy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150735:8"/>from labouringe for their owne Meanes, but ſuch as Preach the Ghoſpell, none who are not Preachers of the Ghoſpell are may be accoumpted Cleargy; But theſe (as before I have proved) were not to be Teachers or Preachers of the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, therefore they were not to be of the Cleargy, but of the Laiety. And that none but thoſe who Preach the Ghoſpell, exempted as Gods Cleargy from labour, may appeare by that which the Apoſtle, 1. Cor. 9, 14 ſaith, in theiſe wordes: So alſo hath the Lord Ordeined, that they which Preach the Ghoſpell ſhould live of the Ghoſpell. And verſe, 6, he ſaith: Or I onely and Barnabas, have not we power not to worke? who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock? Where we ſee, that it is the Miniſtration of the Ghoſpell, that conferrs upon any this Priviledge, that he is not to worke for his livinge, but is to be maintayned of the Charge of Gods People. Now Cleargy is as much as Gods Lot, ſet apart to be maintayned of the Charge of Gods people, for the Service they do to God for others; therefore none but ſuch may be accoumpted Gods Cleargy. Moreover, if the Apoſtle argue for this Priviledge from any ones Preaching the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, how ſhall we vvarrantably eaſe our ſelvs, of that rabble of Popiſh Cleargy, which by corruption of Tradition Popery would thruſt upon us if we underſtande not the Apoſtle here, that onely they who feede the flock by Preaching, are to be accoumpted for Cleargy? If it be now obiected, that Deacons are Cleargy, and yet Deacons Preach not untill they be licenſed, then I anſwer, That Deacons may be reſtreyned, not for that they may not Preach by right, but for that they ſhould firſt be tried and proved, leaſt being yonge Students they preach evell Doctryne through ignorance. And indeede we fyndinge in Scripture, that Deacons remayninge Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons were Preachers, Acts, 6, 8, and, 8, 5, vve may vvell ſay that Deacons as Deacons have right to Preach. But here
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150735:8"/>vve fynde Governours who are not to be Teachers; therefore theiſe cannot claime the Priviledge of Cleargy as may Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</p>
                  <p>I conclvde therefore, that ſeing Gods Cleargy is as his Lot to be maintayned at the Charge of his People: and ſeing the Apoſtle claimes this for Preachinge the vvord, therefore theiſe Governours not being to be Teachers, have no right to be of the Cleargy, but are to be Lay Elders.</p>
                  <p>Againe, ſome may ſay: But muſt ſuch be in every Parriſh Church? I anſwer, yes: For Acts 14, 23. we reade thus: And when they had ordeyned them Elders by Election in every Church, they commended them to the Lord in whom they Beleeved; if then in every Church there were ordeyned a plurality of Elders, ſafeſt it is to have many Elders in every Church. Moreover, ſeinge here it is ſaid that Elders (imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge many) were ordeyned in every Church: and ſeing vve have before proved, that in thoſe tymes there were in the Church, Elders who onely Ruled, and taught not: and ſeing it is not likely that the Apoſtle, would ſo ſoone Charge every Church with many Cleargy; therefore moſt likely it is, that theiſe Elders vvere many, being parte Cleargy for Rulinge and Teachinge, parte Lay Elders ſerving ſo, Rule onely. And indeede, ſeing the Apoſtle commended the Churches to the Lord, it argues, that he had furniſhed them with ſuch Elders, as in thoſe tymes vvere ordeyned by God to be in the Church; but I have before proved, that God ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Governours who were not Teachers, aſwell as Teachers who alſo Governed; therefore we may not thinke, that the Apoſtle left theiſe Churches defective in either of theiſe. Furthermore, ſeing every Congregation is neceſſarily to have a Teaching Elder, (for, ſhould a flock be without a Shephearde) every Congregation is likewiſe to have ſuch Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Officers as are under Teachers; for though every
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150735:9"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150735:9"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150735:10"/>Congregation be not to have thoſe Offices above Teachers, and which are ſet over Teachers, ſuch as are Biſhops, and Arch-Biſhops, yet, ſuch Offices as are under Teachers every Congregation is neceſſarily to have.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, ſeinge a Parriſh Church cannot be denied to be a church, therefore neceſſarily it ought to have in it, as Elders to Teach, ſo Elders to Rule onely: for the defect in either of theiſe, would ſurely produce a defect in the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the ſame. For this cauſe we may not content our ſelvs with our Civill Lavvyers onely, ſeinge they are not in every Church, but onely in the whole church of a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and in the Biſhops courte onely. Neither may we take our Church vvardens and Side Men for theiſe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, ſeinge they have not Power of Iudgement and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; vvhereas Goverment is lame of one hand if it have not this Power. Surely therefore, accordinge to Gods Ordinance, every church which hath any Elders in it, is to have a Goverment by Elders, but Governinge implies power of Iudginge and Puniſhinge, therefore every church is to have this power in it, as it vvill not be defective in its Goverment. Verily, if we looke upon our people in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, obſervinge their life and converſation in every Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, vve may well ſay that here vvants the Goverment in overy Parriſh which here we ſee the Lord ordeined For, our people for the moſt parte, contentinge themſelves to come to church onely, and ſatisfye the Lawe by hearinge Divine Service and the vvorde Preached, never make conſcience of livinge alſo thereafter, and this for vvant of feeling neere them the Power of this Pariſhionall Goverment. For vvhilſt at home in their Parriſh they may uſe unchriſtian Liberty in their actions and Talks, ſo long as they keepe themſelvs from ſo offendinge, as that the Lawe takes hold of them, our people are mervailous careleſs of obſervinge in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150735:10"/>their ſpeach, the holy reſtreinte of the Ghoſpell. But if they ſawe neere them in their owne Parriſh, a Teacher, and a Deacon, for Cleargy, and ſome of their Neighbours of the Laiety, havinge Power to call the diſorderly to Accoumptes, and to Puniſh them who live not as the Ghoſpell requires, then, what with the neereneſs of the obſervinge eyes of theſe Governours, and what with the ſence of their power to Iudge &amp; Puniſh them, if they obſerve not the Ghoſpell in their life and Converſation, a holy Awe would fall upon Gods people in every Parriſh, cauſinge an abſtayninge from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely Acts and Converſation. And this much the rather, becauſe theiſe Governours dwellinge here and there among them, they are neere in every quarter of the Parriſh, to have knowledge of ſuch as make no conſcience to live and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe as beſeemeth Chriſtians. Therefore aſwell for the utility to Gods people, which vvould ariſe by the havinge in every Parriſh, diverſe of the Antient, godly, and honeſt of the Laiety, to Governe in the Parriſh, as for this evidence from Scripture, that ſuch vvere ordeined in every Church, we ſhould be moved to receave willingely, the ordeyning of ſuch in every Parriſh Church. If it be obiected, <hi>that here every City, not every Church is meant,</hi> then I anſwere, That in thoſe tymes it is likely, that ſome Cityes had but one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and beinge ſo, then to ſay of them, every City, or every Church, is to one effect; neither truly is it likely, that ſo ſoone every City affoorded many Churches. Moreover, ſeinge it was Churches, not Cityes, that were to be thus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, we are rather to underſtande every Church, then every City for theiſe reaſons I conclude, that it is ſafeſt and moſt proffitable, that every Parriſh-Church have ordeyned in it, Lay Elders to Governe onely, aſwell as Cleargy Elders, who both are to Teach and Governe. If it be ſaid, <hi>that every Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Church havinge Cleargy Elders, as, a Teacher or Paſtor, and a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150735:11"/>Deacon, then thus Scripture makes nothinge for Lay Elders,</hi> then to this I anſwere, That ſeinge there is evidence, that in thoſe tymes there were Elders which Ruled and Taught, and Elders which Ruled onely and taught not, therefore fitteſt it is, that here we underſtande not a plurality of Cleargy Elders onely, but rather parte Cleargy part Laiety.</p>
                  <p>Againe, ſome may ſay, <hi>How many muſt they be in Number?</hi> I anſwere, ſeinge we reade of Elders ordeyned, without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge alſo any ſet Number, therefore the Church is not bounde to obſerve any ſet or certaine Number. As the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh therefore is more or leſs in circuit of grounde or quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tety of people, ſo theiſe Governours may be more or ſewer: for where a Parriſh is narrow of boundes, though it conteyn much people, yet three or fower of theiſe Governours may ſerve, ſeinge they are neere in neighbourhood to every one of the Parriſh; whereas where the Parriſhe is large of circuit, there it is needefull that they be ſeven or eight, to the end that their dwellinge may be here and there, to be neere to thoſe of the Parriſh in every quarter to obſerve them.</p>
                  <p>Againe, ſome may ſay, <hi>What is their Office?</hi> I anſwere, ſeinge they are called Governours and Rulers, and yet inferior to Teachers, it implies, that they, with, though under the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of a Parriſh, ſhould Governe the people of the Parriſh. And ſeinge Goverment is lame, where Power of Iudginge &amp; Puniſhinge is wantinge, therefore, (as vve would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave the Lord to give a Lame Ordinance to his Church) we are to Beleeve, that theiſe Governours ſhould aſſiſt the Cleargy, in Iudginge and Puniſhinge with eccleſiaſticall Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, ſuch in the Parriſh, as obſerve not the Ghoſpell in their life and converſation. If here it be obiected, <hi>that then I make them: Ministers of the ſame Power in bindinge and looſinge, as the Lord committed to the Cleargy onely;</hi> I anſwere, No; for there is difference betwixt byndinge and looſinge the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150735:11"/>ſinne its ſelfe, and inflictinge or releaſinge of Puniſhments: there is difference betweene byndinge a Man in his ſinne, or looſinge him from it, and puniſhinge a Man with eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Puniſhments for offences, or releaſinge him from the the ſame. And indeede, the worde is, Iohn, 20, 23: <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evers ſinnes ye remit, whoſoevers ſinnes yee retayne;</hi> not whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Puniſhment you inflict or remit; therefore in the firſt of theiſe the Cleargy onely have Power, but in the ſecond, the mixt Elders of the Church, aſwell the Lay as Cleargy El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders have Power. When the inceſtuous Corinthian was to be excommunicated, the Apoſtle commits this to a plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality rather then to any one, 1. Cor. 5, 13: <hi>Put away ther fore from amonge your ſelvs that wicked Man;</hi> And in the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Abſolution he doth the like, 2. Cor. 2, 7: <hi>Ye ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to forgive him.</hi> To conclude then, Theiſe Lay Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours Office is, to joyne with the Cleargy of the Parriſh in obſervinge thoſe of the Parriſh, whither they live and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe as beſeemeth Saincts, and where any are faulty, there to judge of the crime, &amp; to proceede againſt them as the cauſe requireth. If theiſe Governours offend in their Goverment, whither by Negligence, or by untymely Severity, or diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly proceedings, they have over them the Biſhop &amp; Arch-Biſhop, who are to call them to Accoumpt, and to puniſh them alſo for any evell adminiſtration of their office; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo ſo much the rather ſuch Governours may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in every Church and Kingedome, and not oppoſed as in theiſe tymes, as for a dangerous rabble of rude and turbulent Buſy-Bodies. Neither indeede may any be ſuffered to Rule contrary to the Ghoſpell, who have their office by the Ghoſpell, therefore if Paſtors and Biſhops muſt be, 2. Tim. 2, 24, <hi>gentle towards all Men, ſufferinge the evell Men patiently, provinge if God at any time will give them repentance, that they may come to amendment,</hi> how much more ſhould theiſe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150735:12"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150735:12"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150735:13"/>Governours be like minded? For if Goverment and Iuſtice be not hindred by this lenity in Paſtors and Biſhops, why ſhould this preiudice the ſame, if theiſe Governours doe likewiſe? And if Timothie muſt not <hi>receave an Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation againſt an Elder, but under two or three witneſſes, I. Tim. 5, 19,</hi> much leſs muſt theiſe inferior Governours, hand over head trouble Men, upon every reporte they heare, or ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they have. And if the Elders of the Church be ſo to be reſpected, are not the Elders of the Kingedome, even Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Magiſtrates to be likewiſe ſo reſpected? As God ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the Elders of the Church, that every reporte, or every little evidence of evell, ſhall not be preſently taken hold of to their diſgrace, ſo we may well thinke that even ſuch his will is alſo, concerning the Civill Magiſtrats of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; therefore the Governours of the Church ought to be ſlowe in medling with ſuch. S. Peter alſo, 1. Pet 5, 3, chargeth the Elders Church, <hi>that not as though they were Lords over Gods heretage,</hi> they ſhould Governe the ſame. Whilſt this bridle therefore is put into the mouthes of theiſe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and this alſo by the Ordinance of God, theiſe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours neede not ſo to be oppoſed as ſome would have it, under pretence that they woulde prove in the Kingdome, a ſorte of ignorant Men, puffed up by this Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and troublers of men upon every the leaſt occaſion. True it is, that we muſt underſtande, that as the Kingedome, ſo the Church, may not ſo pervert Iuſtice, as not to lay hold on them that ſinne openly; therefore where there is an open ſinninge theiſe may not be timerous, vnder coulour of ſufferinge the evell men patiently. Yea, I ſay more, vvhen it is hearde certainely abroade, (as was that 1. Cor. 5, 1.) that ſuch or ſuch a Man is a Drunkarde, a whore mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, fornicator, Adulterer, extortioner, Railer, filthy ſpeaker, or the like, ſuch fame or report muſt not be neglected, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150735:13"/>rather muſt occaſion a watchinge over ſuch, and when dut Accuſation ſhall ſeconde the Reporte, then may they no neglect to proceede againſt ſuch. To this I may add as a parte of their care and Goverment, that they ſee the Church decently kept, and the Congregation ordered in fit manner, aſwell for order in ſittinge, as for perfourmance of ſuch Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies as ſerue to expreſs Reverence at Divine Service. In a vvorde, they are to ſee that Men live and converſe, as the ordinance of the Ghoſpell, together with the Churches Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons (not diſſonant from the Ghoſpells ordinances) require. Surely the Benefit of ſuch Lay Governours in every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation woulde be greate; for by their Elderly Gravity of yeares, and Authority which ſuch kinde of Elderſhipp onely carries with it: &amp; by the plurality of their Number, and their dwellinge in ſeverall parts of the Parriſh, not onely an Awe of them would fall upon them of that Congregation, but alſo a certainety of crimes would the ſooner be attayned, ſo that men could hardly live longe diſorderly, but they would be knowen ſo to doe to ſome or other of theiſe Governours. Moreover, by ſuch Governours our people would be bette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the Churches State and Maieſty would be increaſed; for our people ſeinge that the Antient amonge them, have Authority even by Gods Ordinance, to obſerve, Governe, Iudge, &amp; puniſh them, they wil be the more carefull to live &amp; converſe as beſeemeth Chriſtians: And the church havinge the Antient of the Laiety in every Congregatiö, joyned with the Cleargy in the Goverment of the churche, &amp; ſervinge as Governours inferior to the Cleargy, the State &amp; Authority of the church would greately be augmented To conclude then, if God ſent out the Ghoſpell accompanied with this kinde of goveruours alſo, (which thing I have before proved from the Scriptures) cann we expect any other then detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yea &amp; puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, if we deny to admit ſuch governours;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150735:14"/>Shall not our Land and Kingedome ſuffer viſitations, for the Neglect and Oppoſinge of ſo holy and neceſſary an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God? Shall the Ghoſpell be admitted, and its Goverment kept out? or cann we expect proffit by the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell if thus vve doe? For doubleſs Iudgements accompany the Ghoſpell, where the Government ordeyned to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it will not be admitted. For the avoidinge of Gods judgements therefore, and for the betteringe of our people, yea for the augmentation of the State and Majeſty of our Church of Englande, let theiſe Lay Elders be admitted, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Eccleſiaſticall Rule and Goverment. To this I may add, that as common experience ſhews, the puttinge Offices of Power and goverment into Mens hands, maketh them growe in kuowledge of the Lawes, and carefull of their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo ſurely the puttinge this Eccleſiaſticall Power and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment into the Elders of the Laiety, would both occaſion their ſearch more diligently into the worde of God, thereby to increaſe their knowledge of the Divine will, and alſo their carefull taking heede unto their Manners, that they give not offence to them whom they are to governe. Yea the yonger Men alſo in every Parriſh, ſeinge the Credit &amp; honor of ſuch place of government, would ſtudy the Scriptures, and take care of their Manners, that ſo they may attaine a fame or good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte for their honeſty and Piety, ſo to be the fitter to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied in ſuch Office of goverment as their turnes may come.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, ſome may ſay, <hi>Muſt theiſe beinge once im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in this Office, ever remaine in this Office, and not be imploied in other Offices of the Kingedome?</hi> I anſwere, firſt, that there is greate difference betweene the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the worde, and the Miniſtration of government onely; the firſt is not to be left off; the ſecond may without offence: For the vvorde of God hath laide no ſuch bond on
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150735:14"/>this as on that. Secondly, ſeinge it would be an inſufferable miſcheife unto Kingedomes, if many of the Elders thereof in every Parriſh, ſhould be wholy exempted from its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in Offices needefull thereunto, therefore we may not conceave, that the Lord would ſend ſuch a Goverment eccleſiaſticall into them, as which ſhould bringe with it ſuch an inconvenience and miſcheife. I conclude therefore, that theiſe Lay Governours are not bounde by the Lord, to continue ever in their Office, but now may ſerve in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment of the Church, and another tyme not.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I (Dread Soveraigne) bene the more prolixe in my wrytinge of theiſe, becauſe this our Church of England doth hitherto rather oppoſe then admit of ſuch; but now havinge ſhowen from the vvorde of God, that of Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance ſuch a kynde of Governours or Rulers are to be in the Church; I humbly petition your Majeſtie, that you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande our Cleargy in whom is the Power to confert eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Powers and Offices, that they exerciſe their Power herein, ordeyninge ſome of the antient and godly of the Laiety, to this Power and Authority in every of our Parriſh Churches. So ſhall you ſurely doe a vvorke, acceptable to God, beneficiall to the Church, and worthy of that great Name which you have raiſed to your ſelfe in the Churches of God. Suffer therefore patiently I humbly pray you, this my petition for the admiſſion of theiſe kynde of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Governours, that ſo the Officers eccleſiaſticall ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God, may be wholy found in this our Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande. I grante that many other Offices may be ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Church, as the Change of tymes, increaſe of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificence of Gods Divine Service, and other like things may occaſion; but theiſe before written of are ſuch as may not be omitted, becauſe they have evidence from the vvorde of God, to by the Ordinance of God Apoſtolically delivered;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150735:15"/>therefore alſo the Cleargy in whom is the power of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are of duty bounde to renewe this Ordinance of the Lords in the Church. But havinge written thus of theiſe eccleſiaſticall governours. I proceede to write of extentions alſo of eccleſiaſticall juriſdictions.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>2. PETITION:</hi> That Pariſhes, Biſhopdomes, and Arch-Biſhopdomes, may be conveniently bounded.</head>
                     <p>SOme of our Pariſhes are ſo ſmall, and withall conteyne in them ſo few people, that neither the Congregation beareth a State befittinge a Church, nor yet cann a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Meanes or Revenewe be raiſed therefrom for a Paſtor and Deacon his aſſiſtant; And on the contrary, ſome other Pariſhes retayninge their very antient boundes, conteyne now (by Gods multiplyinge the people in that place) ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny People, that al cannot at one time conveniently aſſemble in the church. I therefore petition, that the ſmaller be made larger, and thoſe which are too large may be divided, that ſo neither Gods Miniſters be diſcouraged, by the ſmale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Revenewe or Meanes of life, nor Gods people diſhartened from comminge to Church, through want of convenient place, when they come there. Some Pariſhes alſo abounde with ſtrangers, who are but lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for a time, yet in ſuch places proviſion were good to be made, that ſuch may have convenient place in the church, leaſt elſe it occaſion in them, either a wandringe from the Parriſh, or a Neglect to reſorte to any Church at all. It hath in all ages bene ſeene, that Change of condition of things, hath cauſed change of former orderinge of thinges; for it is no diſorder to change the antie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t diſpoſure of things, vvhen to reteyne the ſame brings with it great diſorder and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150735:15"/>detriment. Moreover, though Changes carry with them diffently of perfourmance, yet experience hath declared, that when the Magiſtrates authority concurreth with the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, all difficultyes have readily bene overcome, by the peoples voluntary tendinge their owne Benefit, and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of other. Populous Congregations are ſurely moſt meete, both becauſe a convenient Meanes may be better be raiſed for a Teacher or Paſtor, and a Deacon his aſſiſtant; and alſo a plurality of grave and godly Men may be choſen by turnes, to ſerve in that Parriſh for Governours, accordinge to that which I have written aboue; if therefore ſuch a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude be appointed, as which beinge cloſe ſeated together, &amp; diſpoſed in galleries, the voyce of a Preacher may well be hearde of them, then judge I the Congregation to be duly proportioned. And indeede want of diſpoſinge the roome of the church, as beſt may fit to conteyne a greate multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and this alſo within hearinge the voice of a Teacher, cauſeth that farr fewer aſſemble convenlently then vvere meete; for it is but vaine there to reſorte, where though the church have roome enough, yet uſe cannot be made of it for hearinge the Preacher. True it is that Mens voices are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, neither cann all volces anſwere to the ſerled diſpoſure; but yet if reſpect be had to the ordinary voice of Man, and the Roome fitted accordinge thereto, fitter it is that the defect of voice be ſupplied by ſome helpe, then that the diſpoſure of place for audience be changed. Such Paſtors therefore as have lowe voices, may doe well to ſupply that defect with oftner Preachinge, that ſo at one time ſome, at another time others of the Parriſh may conveniently heare them. Theiſe things I write of our Parriſhes in populous Cityes, vvhere the neereneſs of dwellinge, and multitude of ſtrangers lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, cauſeth a very great Congregation in a ſmale quantity of grounde; but in the Country, where in a very large circuite
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150735:16"/>of grounde are but few inhabitants, the proffit of the people rather then State of a Congregation is to be tendered, leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by too long leangth and difficulty of way, people be diſhart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from reſortinge to Church. Surely the former diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of theiſe things in this Lande was very good, accordinge to the times, and we in theiſe tymes neede the leſs alteration, ſave where the Parriſh is too ſmale to yeild a convenient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venewe, or elſe too great to aſſemble within hearinge of a Preacher. Thus havinge written of our Parriſh-boundes, I pray that I may write alſo of the bouudes of our Biſhopp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks and Arch biſhoppricks.</p>
                     <p>If Arch-Biſhhopps ſucceede in the Office of Timothy &amp; Titus, meete it is that they execute in the Church that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; therefore the bounds of their Charge ſhould be ſuch, as wherein conveniently that weighty Charge may be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them. And indeede it is fitter to reſpect rather, the Proffit of the due execution of the Charge, then the Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cality of the Biſhop; though both are to be tendered, yet the former rather then the latter.</p>
                     <p>Now, that Arch-Biſhopps propperly, rather then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, ſucceede in the Office of Timothy and Titus, I gather from this evidence: Firſt, becauſe Titus had intruſted unto him by the Apoſtle, <hi>the Charge and Care of diverſe Cityes and their Churches,</hi> Titus, 1.5: Secondly, becauſe the Scripture ſhews by many perticulers, that the Office of Titus, and the Office of Timothy was one and the ſame; but the Office beinge the ſame, the extention of the Charge over diverſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes may alſo be the ſame: Thirdly, becauſe the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with one voice, did ever accoumpt of the Offices of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy and Titus to be a like: Laſtly, becauſe the antient Chriſtian Church, allowed of the Charge of one over di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Cityes and their Churches and Officers, as an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Apoſtolically delivered to the church: and in antient
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150735:16"/>tyme ſuch were called Arch-Biſhopps; which alſo was a Name very antiently given even to the Biſhop of Rome himſelfe. Theiſe thiugs conſidered I conclude, that in aſmuch as now, and in the moſt antient tymes, Arch-Biſhops have and had the Charge of the Churches in diverſe Cityes, therefore they propperly ſucceede in the Office of Timothy and Titus: For ſurely City-Biſhops never had the Charge of diverſe ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, but onely of one city, and ſome circuit of ground there, about at moſt. This therefore I now petition your ſacred Maieſtie for, that in Englande, the Office or Charge of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy and Titus, be required of our Arch-Biſhops to be executed by them in this Church: and that the bounds of their Iuriſdiction be ſo limited, that conveniently they may execute that Charge. And for the Charge, I rather have an eye to that which I fynde in the Epiſtles of Timothy and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, then to the Canons of the Church in after tyme: for the firſt I am ſure are neceſſarye dutyes, for which the Officer is anſwereable to God; whereas the latter are not of like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſave onely that they may be wholeſome Ordinances, ſo farr fourth as they are accordant to the evidence of ſacred Scripture. The charge which we fynde given to Timothy and Titus, is a Charge to ſee all of all ſorts to live accordinge to the Ghoſpell, and obſerve the Ordinances of God given to the Church by the Apoſtles; therefore his Charge ſtreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to private Chriſtians, to ſee that they live as the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell requires, and alſo to all Officers of the Church, to ſee that they be choſen ſuch as are appointed, &amp; perfourme their Offices righty in the Church. Which great Charge that it may the better be effected, the Apoſtle intruſted him with Power, <hi>to commande things that are right, and to receave Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations againſt them that doe evell, and to ſilence Teachers of evell things, and reiect heretiques,</hi> 1. Tim, 4, 12. 1, Tim, 5, 14. Titus, 1, 11. Titus, 3, 12. Many perticulars are ſet downe in thoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150735:17"/>two Epiſtles, which I wil obbreviate as I may in this manner: in the firſt Epiſtle to Timothy, <hi>The place of aboade is aſsigned,</hi> Chap. 1, 3: <hi>He hath the Charge of other Teachers, that they teach none other Doctryne then they ought,</hi> Chap. 1, 4: <hi>That heede be not given to thinges that breede queſtions, and brawlinges, rather then godly edifyinge,</hi> Chap. 1, 4: <hi>That there be an Order of Divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, or Service,</hi> chap 2, 1, <hi>That women be ſilent in the Church,</hi> Chap. 2, 12: <hi>That Biſhops be ſuch and ſuch, and doe ſo and ſo,</hi> chap. 3, 1: <hi>That Deacons likewiſe be ſuch and ſuch, and doe ſo and ſo,</hi> chap. 3, 8: <hi>That he put all in remembrance of Apostolicall Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trynes,</hi> chap. 4, 6: <hi>That the Church be not unneceſſarily burthened with Charge,</hi> chap. 5, 16: <hi>That he rebuke them openly that ſinne,</hi> chap. 5, 20: <hi>That he have care of layinge on of hands,</hi> chap, 5, 22: <hi>That Elders who Rule well be honoured,</hi> chap, 5, 17: <hi>That the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders who not onely Rule, but Teach alſo, be both honoured and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned,</hi> chap. 5, 18: In the ſecond Epiſtle, He is warned <hi>againſt thoſe who havinge-itchinge eares, will get them Teachers after their owne luſts,</hi> chap. 4, 3: <hi>That he muſt doe the worke of an Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt,</hi> chap. 4, 5. In the Epiſtle to Titus: <hi>That be redreſs things,</hi> Chap. 1, 5: <hi>That he ordeyne Elders,</hi> chap. 1, 3: <hi>That he ſilence Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of evell thinges,</hi> chap, 1, 10: <hi>That obedience be yeilded to Principalities and Powers,</hi> chap. 3, 1: <hi>That fooliſh queſtions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and brawlinges be ſtaied,</hi> chap. 3, 4: <hi>That Hereticks be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,</hi> chap. 3, 10. Many other are the perticulers of this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers Charge, as to ſee <hi>that Servants behave themſelvs as they ought towards their Maſters,</hi> Titus, 2, 9: <hi>That Elder Men and Women be ſo and ſo, and the yonger Men and Women likewiſe:</hi> and other like; beſides <hi>his owne private Miniſtration of the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</hi> Now therefore, if the perticulers whereto this Officers Office ſtreatcheth, be duly conſidered, let any judge, if our Arch-Biſhopps bounds in England be convenient for the due executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For to what end hath a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charge of theiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulers, if both he be not conveniently neere to viſit places,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150735:17"/>and ſee to the obſervation of theiſe things, and alſo that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations againſt diſobedience be not conveniently to be made unto him? If one Arch-Biſhop ſhould be ſet over all England, were it ſufficient? coulde he conveniently exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this Charge in the church? neither truly cann two; therefore Arch-Biſhops ſhould be multiplied, that ſo the Lande may have ſo many, as well may ſerve for the due exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of this high Charge.</p>
                     <p>True it is, that Crete is an yle of greate circuit of grounde, and conteyned in old tyme many moe cityes then in theiſe tymes it doth; but reſpect is tobe had unto the tymes; for difference is to be put betweene tymes, when but few in a Lande are converted to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, and when all the people of a Lande are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. When few are converted, the Congregations or chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are the fewer, and conſequently the Charge is the leſs, and the better to be executed, but when all are converted, then, as neceſſarily the Churches are multiplied ſo alſo is tho Charge increaſed, and conſequently the dutyes of the Office are made the more diſticult to be executed in all.</p>
                     <p>Neither is it probable, nor is it likely, that in the time of Titus, all the people in that yle of Crete vvere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the faith; but if they vvere not, then to retayne in the Succeſſors hands the ſame extent of grounde as had Titus, were to commit to the leſs able Succeſſor, a greater charge of Churches then the Apoſtle intruſted to Titus: vvhich thinge cannot be done, without great preiudice to the Chriſtian church.</p>
                     <p>As Pariſhes therefore are to be multiplled, and one to be made tvvo or three, after the people growe too many for one Congregation, ſo antient Arch-Biſhoppdomes boundes ſhoulde be leſsned, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150735:18"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150735:18"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150735:19"/>one divided into three or fower, when the People make too many Churches to be intruſted unto one Arch-Biſhopp. I moſt humbly pray your Majeſtie therefore, that the perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers of the Office be duly conſidered, and then that the bounds of our Archiepiſcopall luriſdictions may be fitted thereunto. Doubtleſs if our Arch-Biſhops tooke care as they ought of the perticulers of this Charge, they woulde ſoone make a holy People in this Lande, by reaſon of their neere eye to obſerve the ſeverall Churches, and their recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge Accuſations when neede requireth. And truly the Arch-Biſhops Courte ſhould not be ordeyned ſo much, for ſome perticulers tendinge to the Rule over other Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, as it ſhould be for the correctinge of diſobediences in all theiſe perticulers, when neither in the Pariſhionall, nor in the Epiſcopall Courte and Goverment order is taken in the ſame: For the Archiepiſcopall Charge is no leſs, to ſee Evangelicall Ordinances obſerved in the Manners of every particuler Chriſtian, then to ſee that Paſtors and Biſhops, &amp; other eccleſiaſticall Officers, execute their Miniſtrations rightly.</p>
                     <p>I grant, that Pariſhionall, and over them Epiſcopall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verments, greatly eaſe the Arch-Biſhop, and becauſe of them his Charge may be very large, compriſinge diverſe Biſhopdomes; but yet with this caution, that he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently viſit every parte, and alſo from all parts Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations may conveniently be made unto him; when there is any faile in the Pariſhional and Epiſcopall Goverment. Neither truly ought Arch-Biſhopdoms to be extended out as Kingedomes: For Kingedomes are in larged or reſtrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as their Power cann extend its ſelfe, which alſo is ordered by God himſelf, he letting looſe and reſtreyninge the Powers as he will; whereas Arch Biſhopdoms ought to be fitted to the execution of the Charge of the Office. Thus have I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150735:19"/>(Dread Soveraigne) bene the longer in my wrytinge of Arch-Biſhopps, becauſe of the neceſſary conſequence, that if they be made leſs, then Biſhopdomes alſo ſhould not bee too large, becauſe diverſe of them are to be compriſed in one Arch Biſho-dome. For Biſhopdomes therefore I in breife pray, that in our England they may be more, that ſo they not compriſinge over many Patiſhes, the Biſhop may conveniently viſit the perticuler Pariſhes, and Accuſations conveniently be made out of all Pariſhes which faile in Goverment, unto him. The Biſhop differeth from the Arch-Biſhop cheiſely in this, that his Charge ſtreatcheth not over other City Biſhops, but onely over Biſhops or Paſtors and other Cleargy of perticuler Congregations. As for other differences which the Canons of the Church have put, they are neceſſary as the tymes require onely: For the Churches Ordinances have ever bene diſpenced with, in caſes of Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity when they could not be obſerved, and when there is no more needefull uſe of the ſame; but this difference which here I put, ſeemes to be a Divine Ordinance, in aſmuch as Titus was ſet over diverſe Cityes and the churches therein, &amp; conſequently over all eccleſiaſticall Officers vvhich neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily are in them. But then if the Arch-Biſhopps Charge ſtreacheth to Man and Wife, Parents and Children, Maſters and Servants, ſeinge to it that they in their Manners one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde another, obſerve the commandements of the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, ſhould not the Biſhops Office within his perticuler li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſtreatch to the ſame? Therefore I humbly pray, that our Biſhops Office be not ſtreigtned unto ſome few perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers, but that it be enlarged to ſee even to all theiſe things alſo, as the moſt weighty perticulers of his Charge. Which thinge duly conſidered, I hope it will ſoone appeare, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily (for the due ſeinge unto theiſe things, and for the convenient makinge of Accuſations of breach of them,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150735:20"/>vvhere the Pariſhionall Goverment is remiſs, not takinge due Care of, and order in ſuch things) our Biſhops juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are to be made leſs, then at this time they are in this our Church of Englande. Doubtleſs theiſe Powers and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces eccleſiaſticall were cheifely ordeyned, for Rulinge of the Manners of Chriſtian people, leaſt they not obſervinge one towards another the Evangelicall Commandements, bringe a ſcandall upon the Ghoſpell of Chriſte; therfore into theiſe thinges ſhould our Biſhops watchfully looke, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves with the obſervation of Eccleſiaſticall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons onely. If any ſay, that the deſcription of this Office is in Scripture ſuch, as is rather to be wiſhed then effected, I anſwere, that the Apoſtle would not ſo deepely Charge Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy with theiſe perticulers as he doth, 1. Tim, 5, 21, if he thought the execution of theiſe things to be rather to be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed then effected; therefore I hope none ſhall be ſuffered to ſhrowde their Negligence, under the mantle or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of this deviſe. If in after tymes many inventions are made, to buſy Atch-Biſhopps &amp; Biſhopps ſo with them, that they cannot attend to theiſe other, are theiſe which are the weightleſt to be left for the lighter? Shall honor and Glory attend rather thoſe then theiſe? were not this a notable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, a ſnare of Satan, and an inſufferable divertion from the true Epiſcopall dutyes? But now (my moſt gratious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne) in hope of your reproofe of ſuch things, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandinge and honoringe theiſe the cheifeſt epiſcopall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, I paſs from writinge of the boundings and Iuriſdictions, unto my Petition, for your freeinge our Cleargy here, from forreiue and unlawfull Eccleſiaſticall Powers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:150735:20"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>3. PETITION:</hi> That your Majeſtie continue to free this Church, from all forreine and unlawfull Eccleſiaſticall uſurpations and Powers.</head>
                     <p>THe permiſſion of inconvenient extents of Iuriſdiction, hath bene the cheife cauſe, not onely of the diſorders of Eccleſiaſticall Politie, and of the evell execution of true Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall Charges, but alſo of the Antichriſts Reigninge in the Church; therefore high tyme it is that in the Churches Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, this maine error be taken order for. It is reported of that firſt great &amp; famous Councill of Nice, that it confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the Biſhops of certaine cityes, the huge extents which formerly their Charge had ſtreatched its ſelfe unto; but what followed hereupon? ſurely there followed not onely the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulency of ſuch great Powers, and the inſatiable affectation of Glory, but alſo the openinge or reveilinge of that Man of ſinne. For as the Apoſtle ſaid, 2. Theſſal. 2, 6: <hi>And now ye knowe what withholdeth, that he might be reveiled in his tyme,</hi> ſo indeede it fell out; for the Emperors keepinge his Seate at Rome, withheld the Biſhopp of Romes Reveilinge; but the Emperor removinge his Seate to Conſtantinople, this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of Nice ſome few yeares after was aſſembled, where theiſe huge extents of Iuriſdiction beinge confirmed, the Biſhop of Rome beinge held as Cheife of them, this cauſed his firſt meaſure of Reveilinge. It is fit therefore that that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils proceedings be examined, whither in oughts God left it to diſſent from his ſacred Worde. Papiſts uſually alleadge that Councill, as countenancinge the offeringe up of the Body and Blood of the Lord in the Service of the Lords Supper; but if this that Councill did, then expreſsly erred it
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150735:21"/>from the Scriptureis nſtruction concerninge that Service. And how neere it was to forbid Preiſts, the copulation with their vvives vvhich Gods worde commandes, 1. Cor, 7, 3, is well knowen to all that have read the Story of thoſe tymes. To this I may add, the uncertainety of its Canons, ſeinge they are with ſuch uncertainety brought us by Tradition. For all theiſe reaſons I conclude, that that Councill is not ſo to be maintayned in its Ordinances, as that the inſtruction of ſacred Scripture is not rather to be followed. But who that looketh into the holy Scripture ſhall not ſee, That Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy and Titus &amp; ſuch as were like them, held the higheſt ordinary Offices in the Church next unto the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs? for by the Epiſtles of Timothy and Titus it is evident, that the Apoſtle ſet them in Office next himſelfe over the Churches that were planted. Churches were planted, and they had their Officers and Governours, but then the Apoſtle ordeyned theiſe over them againe, and this is manifeſt in that Titus had Charge over diverſe Cityes. Whilſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is this evidence for their Office: and whilſt there is that evidence before noted, that our Arch-Biſhops ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede them in that Office: and vvhilſt the Church ever held a ceſſation of Apoſtles, and the Apoſtle, 1. Cor. 4, 9, ſaith: <hi>I thinke that God hath ſet fourth us the laſt Apoſtles, &amp;c:</hi> We have good reaſon, not to ſuffer other offices to uſurpe Authority over Arch-Biſhops; or any Arch-Biſhopps to be ſubiugated unto any other Eccleſiaſticall Miniſtration. But if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the continuance of thoſe huge extents whereof we read, then, as neceſſarily many Arch-Biſhopdomes, yea Patriarch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes muſt be compriſed therein, ſo the Biſhop of that Seate muſt be advanced over, and exerciſe a Miniſtration ovet Arch-Biſhopps, yea over Patriarchs; which thinge what is it, but both an evertion of the Politie eccleſiaſticall, which God by his Ordinance (Apoſtles taken away) ſent the church
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150735:21"/>withall under the Wings of Kinges and Princes: and alſo a bringinge in Superiorityes, Throanes, and Powers, never or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned by the Lord? As therefore experience hath ſhowen, that when an Arch-Biſhoprick hath neceſſarily bene divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, then tvvo Arch-Biſhops are placed therein, without ſubiugating the one under the other, ſo thoſe antient extents of bounds, ought with the increaſe of the Convertion of people, to have bene divided into many Arch-Biſhopdomes, and this without ſubiugatinge every of them to the Arch-Biſhopp of ſome one city, who by this meanes, as he is to take a New Title, ſo alſo he entereth into a new Miniſtration never ordeyned by the Lord.</p>
                     <p>If any ſay, hath not every Sncceſſor right, to retayne the bownds of his predeceſſors juriſdiction? I anſwere, yes, where there is no prejudice thereby to the Church, and to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God; but when retayninge the ſame, he muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily Rule over them, whom God by his Ordinance ſet next unto Apoſtles, he then ſubverts the Ordinance of God, ſo longe as he cannot make himſelfe an Apoſtle. Neither cann any ones ſucceedinge in the Seate of an Apoſtle, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr upon him an Apoſtles Dignity and Office: for this were to make ſuch a one an Apoſtle; but we have good cauſe to aſke of ſuch a one the ſignes of his Apoſtleſhip, 2. Cor. 12, 12. I conclude therefore, that thoſe extents of Iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which carry with them a bringinge into the Church, Powers and Miniſtrations above that of Arch-Biſhops, are unlawfull, as bringinge into the Church ſtrange Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which have no manner warrant from Gods Worde in Scripture, but rather are contrary to the Politie which there God manifeſteth to his Church. And indeede becauſe of the huge extent of the Pope of Romes juriſdiction, we fynde that above Arch Biſhopps are Patriarchs, as alſo Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls (as now Cardinalls are) &amp; Popes Legats, and a rabble
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150735:22"/>of other, who all ſerve rather as Miniſters of this Corruption of Eccleſiaſtical Politie warranted by God, then of the church, &amp; of the Ghoſpell. For how many are the Officers which the Pope of Rome needeth for to ſerve him only, in the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo large a juriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as now he exerciſeth? even ſo propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably is it with every Patriarch, yea with every Arch-Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop when he hath a Iuriſdiction ſo farr extended fourth, as that neither he can perſonally viſit conveniently the parts of his Charge, nor they of his Charge cann conveniently make Accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s unto him, if the Pariſhional or Epiſcopal Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments faile in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iuſtice. But now, ſeinge God hath given ſo bleſſed Teſtimony, to the Reforminge of things by his worde in Scripture, why ſhould not ſuch Offices be cut off, as ſuperfluous and juſtly Offenſive, which exerciſe any Authority over the Arch-Biſhops of the Chriſtian church? Should we not thinke that the Lord expects a Reformation even herein, aſwell as in Doctryne? Should not his vvords direction be of power with us, aſwell in Reforminge errors of Iuriſdictions, or Powers &amp; Offices, as in reforminge of Doctrynes? Therefore if the Scripture ſhew, that the Offices of Timothy &amp; Titus, was the higheſt ordinary Office in the Church, after Apoſtles ceaſed, as beinge in the life tyme of the Apoſtles next to the Apoſtles: and if there be good evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that thoſe had under them at the moſt but Biſhopps of Cityes, then why ſhould not Arch-Biſhopps be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as Succeeders into their Office, and conſequently to be the higheſt eccleſiaſticall Officer, which God ſent the Church with amonge the Nations, after his taking away of Apoſtles? If it be ſaid, that thoſe who ſucceeded into the Seates of Timothy or Titus, and others like them, are Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, not Arch-Biſhopps, then I demande, what Manner Biſhops cann any prove that either Timothy or Titus, or the next Succeſſors ruled over? whither were they Arch-Biſhos
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150735:22"/>or onely Biſhopps of Cityes? Surely, the greateſt evidence of pureſt and moſt antient Tradition is, that thoſe of thoſe Seates were firſt accoumpted but Arch-Biſhops, and though they ſeemed to have Charge of a greate circuit of grownde, yet where any Arch-Biſhop was ordeyned, I fynde not any good evidence, that they exerciſed Authority over them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as now Patriarchs doe over them, and the Pope over Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches. As for the extendinge out of Care, or ſeeminge-Charge of the Churches in greate extent, we fynde in antient tyme, not onely an affectation, but alſo a reall effectinge, of chalenginge the Charge of all thoſe Churches, whereunto ſome Biſhop of ſpeciall Accoumpt ſtreatched his Adviſe &amp; Counſalle: as if over all, to whom Adviſe and Counſaile is given, the giver of Adviſe &amp; Counſalle ſhould have Charge, &amp; over the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exerciſe Epiſcopall Authority. If thus the Biſhops of thoſe tymes did, (and ſome evidence there is that ſome ſo did) then this is no ſufficient warrant, for chalenginge of ſo exceſſive charges or Iuriſdictions as ſome Patriarchs &amp; Arch-Biſhops chalenge; much leſs ſhould we admit of ſuch exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, when we ſee that it is diſcordant to the Ordinance of God, as I have before ſhewed. Moreover, if the Councill of Nice approved of ſuch large &amp; exceſſive extents of Care and Iuriſdiction in any, yet we are to thinke, that it but Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that Iuriſdiction which they then had; but at that tyme the extentions of Inriſdiction were not ſo large as in after tyme. Had the Pope of Rome then ſuch Iuriſdiction as now, when no parte of Germany, nor other Nations had embraced the faith as ſince they did? Or ſhould we thinke that that Councill ſubiugated to that Biſhop, Churches not as then propagated? If no, then neither by warrant of holy Scripture, nor by warrant of that Councill, hath that Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop any right of Iuriſdiction over all the Arch-Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopps of all the Chriſtian Nations in the Weſt:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150735:23"/>As for claime as Succeſſor to the Apoſtle Peter, it is ſtrange that he alone, ſhould make a claime of ſucceedinge to an Apoſtle; for where be the other Biſhops, who claime to ſucceede to this or that Apoſtle? I fynde none but him of Antioch: and that alſo rather a figment of the Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Romes, then any true claime of that Biſhops. And as for his claime from Scripture, I have elſew here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it to be directly againſt that which our Lord commanded to his Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p>Theiſe things conſidered, I now humbly beſeech yourſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſtie, that as hitherto you have ſhowen great favour to our Cleargy, ſo you will continue to preſerve them from any forreine and unlawfull eccleſiaſticall Powers, which would chalenge Authority over them. Princes may doe well to have an eye at the vviſedome, and gratious Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, obſervinge with what Powers eccleſiaſticall he (Apoſtles taken away) ſent the Church under their wings: For ſurely there cann be no better Politie of eccleſiaſticall Goverment for Princes, then that which we fynde the Lord to leave in the Church, after his takinge away of Apoſtles. Should the Lord ſend any Officet under the wings of Princes, who ſhould ſtreatch his Authority farr further, then any Prince cann ſtreatch his vvings of protection? Or ſhould one Biſhopp be under the vvings of many Princes protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? vvhat then if thoſe Princes fall at variance, ſhall the one protect his Adverſaries ſubiecte?</p>
                     <p>Therefore I cannot but conclude, that as it is not good for the Church, ſo it is alſo in convenient &amp; dangerous for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that there be in the church any Eccleſiaſtical Miniſters of huge extents of Iuriſdiction, ſuch as are ſome Patriarchs, and the Pope of Rome.</p>
                     <p>Thus havinge written at large of theiſe things, becauſe our tymes greately neede the ſo doinge, I now cloſe up this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150735:23"/>Chapter, and my notes upon the former Scriptures collected. prayinge that I may proceede to other.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>II. CHAP.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OF King Hezekias we reade, 2, Chron, 31, 4: That he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the people that dwelt in Hieruſalem, to give a part to the Preiſts and Levits, that they might be in couraged in the Lawe of the Lord And when the Commandement was ſpread, the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell brought abondaunce of firſt fruicts, of Corne, and Wine, and Oile, and Hony, and of all the increaſe of the Feild, and the Tithes of all things brought they aboundantly. And Hezekias queſtioned the Preiſts and the Levits, concerning the Heapes. And Azariah the cheife Preiſt, of the houſe of Zadock, anſwered him, and ſaid, ſince the people begann to bringe the Offerings into the houſe of the Lord, we have eaten, and have bene ſatisfied, and there is left in aboundannce. And Hezekias commaunded to prepare Chambers in the houſe of the Lord, and they prepared them, and caried in the firſt fruicts, and the tythes, and the dedicate thinges faithfully. And over them was Coniah the Levite the cheife, and Shimei his brother the ſecond. And Core the Sonne of Imnah the Levite Porter toward the eaſt, was over the things that were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingely offered unto God, to diſtribute to their Brethren the Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, and the holy things that were conſecrate, their daily portions. Againe, of Kinge Ioſias we reade, 2. Chron, 34, 8: That he ſent Shafan and Maaſeiah the Governour of the City, and Ioah the Recorder, to repaire the houſe of the Lord. And when they came to Hilkia the high Preiſt, they delivered the money that was brought into the houſe of God, which the Levits that kept the dore had gathered, at the hands of Manaſſch and Ephraim, and of all the reſidue of Iſrael, and of all Iudas and Beniamin, and of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150735:24"/>inhabitants of Hieruſalem. And they put it into the hands of them which ſhould doe the worke. Againe, Exodus, 36; 3, we reade thus: And they received of Moſes all the Offeringes, which the Children of Iſrael had brought, for the worke of the ſervice of the Sanctuary to make it: Alſo they brought ſtill unto him free Gifts every morninge. So all the wiſe men that wrought all the holy worke, came every Man from his worke which they had wrought, and ſpake to Moſes, ſaying: The people bringe too much, and more then enough for the uſe of the worke, which the Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be made. Then Moſes gave a Commandement, and they cauſed it to be proclaimed throughout the hoſte, ſaying: Let neither Man nor Woman, prepare any more worke for the Oblation of the Sanctuary. So the people were staied from Offeringe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In theiſe Scriptures I note theiſe fower things ſpecially: Firſt, That the Kinge commanded the People, to give to the Maintenance of the Miniſters: Secondly, That Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is for their incouragement to ſerve in the Miniſtery: Thirdly, That the Kinge cared alſo for the Repairinge of the Churches, wherein God was vvorſ hipped: Laſtly, That when there was a Sufficiency, this was to be acknowledged by the Cleargy, and the People were to be ſtaied from giving; According to which obſervations, I humbly pray, that I may petition your ſacred Majeſtie, as hereunder ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
                  <p>It beinge the Commandement and Ordinance of God, 1. Cor. 9, 14, that the Miniſters of the Ghoſpell be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned by them to whom they Miniſter the Ghoſpell, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are bounde to fynde them Maintenance, if they be not bounde alſo to maintayne them by Tythes, firſt fruicts, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will Offeringes, and the like. But where the Manner of doinge is not appointed by God, vvhen yet the thinge to be done is appointed, there Gods Miniſters of Rule and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150735:24"/>have Power to appointe the Manner of doinge, and none may lawfully except againſt the Manner which they appointe. In this church of England then, your Majeſtics famous Predeceſſors havinge ordeyned, and your ſelfe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly confirmed, that the Miniſters Maintenance be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Tythinge of your people, I moſt humbly pray, that the full Tythes of the Lande be given to the Lords Cleargy. Doubtleſs (dread Soveraigne) the permiſſion of Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, where, not the Cleargy, but Lay perſons reape the Tythes, cauſeth both a diſcouragement to Gods Cleargy, through want of convenient Maintenance in ſuch Pariſhes: and alſo a ſcantery of able Miniſters to ſerve the Lord in thoſe places. And truly it is lamentable to obſerve, both how poorely ſome Cleargy are faine to live, even there where they execute the Office of their Miniſtry, and where a Lay Man gathers ſuch a quantery of Tythes, as would ſerve for a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Maintenance for one or two of the Cleargy: and alſo how many Miniſters, painefull in Preachinge the Ghoſpell, after they have vvorne out their life in poverty, leave their vvife and children (well neere) to beggery. But ſeinge it is Gods Lawe that his Cleargy may marry, 1. Tim. 1, 2: and ſeinge it is likewiſe his Lawe, that the married yeild due be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence, 1. Cor. 7, 3, meete it is, that the Cleargyes portions be ſuch, as that they may (with thrift) lay up alſo for their Wife and children. Yea, the Apoſtle in ſayinge, 2. Cor. 12, 14: <hi>for the Children ought not to lay up for the fathers, but the fathers for the Children,</hi> implies a Neceſſity laid upon all fathers, and amonge them ſuch of the Cleargy as have children, that they provide and lay up for their children; therefore ſuch Cleargy as keepe ſuch Hoſpitality, as ſpendes the Revenewe of their livings, are rather to be blamed then commended, whilſt withall they lay not up for their vvife and children. Moreover, ſeinge it were moſt unbefittinge Chriſtians, to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150735:25"/>villify the Miniſters of the Ghoſpell in maintenance, whom they are to have in honor for the Miniſtration of the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, moſt meete it is, that every Pariſ hes allowance, every Biſhopdomes, and Arch-Biſhopdomes allowance be ſuch, as may ſerve for to maintayne each of the Cleargy, in ſuch ranck and faſhion as beſt beſeemeth; therefore as our Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Arch-Biſhops have place of eminency and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity amonge our Nobles, ſo the Paſtors of Congregations are to have ſuch Maintenance as may in able them to beare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, rather with the better then with the meaner ſorte in each Parriſh. As for our Biſhops and Arch-Biſhops, their Maintenance is already commendably greate, through the large Bounty of our fore-fathers, and your Majeſties confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what they now injoy thereof; but becauſe I have in the former Chapter intreated, for the multiplyinge of the number of Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops in this Church, I now humbly petition your Majeſtie, that I may move unto one thinge which would be needefull. If it be neceſſary that there be more Biſhopricks and Arch-Biſhopricks in Englande, then now there are, (and this I have proved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) then it followes neceſſarily that Maintenance alſo be increaſed. I therefore petition, That unto that which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready our Biſhops have among them, there may be added a taxe upon all the People of the Lande, that every houſe-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der contribute a ſmale yearely Gift to his Biſhop, and an other ſmale Guift to the Arch-Biſhop in whoſe Province he is; for by the multitude of families in a Biſhopdome, a ſmale matter raiſed from every family, would affoorde a very greate portion to the Biſhop: and by the multitude of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in an Arch-Biſhopprick, the like greate portion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably would ariſe to the Arch-Biſhop. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Biſhop and the Arch-Biſhop woulde be the more bounde, to have care of, and (vvithout Charge) often to viſit
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150735:25"/>privately, the ſeverall Pariſhes, ſeinge to it that all things be therein accordinge as they ought to be: for it cannot vvell be that they ſhould neglect them, when halfe yearely or quarterly they are put in mynde of them by their Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence unto them. And verily, better it is for Gods people, accordinge to their ſeverall conditions of quallity, to parte vvith an eaſy payment, of ſix pence, or a ſhillinge quarterly, or more or leſs, to their Biſhop and Arch-Biſhop, that here-through their Iuriſdictions being the ſmaller, they may prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably execute in them their ſeverall Miniſtrations accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to Gods Ordinance, then for want hereof to ſuffer them to injoy ſo large and ſpatious Iuriſdictions for Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cality and Revenewe, as that they doe not, nor conveniently cann, execute rightly their ſeverall dutyes and Offices. I grant that every Pariſhes Charge is already greate, by the payinge of Tithes, or other ſomes of mony, towards the Maintenance of the Cleargy of their ſeverall Pariſhes; but yet, for ſo good and proffitable an occaſion as is this, they ſhall doe Chriſtianly to beare moreover a ſmale taxe for their Biſhop, and another for their Arch-Biſhop.</p>
                  <p>Greate was the bounty of our Predeceſſors in this kynde, and this alſo done even under Popery; and ſhall we then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyinge a moſt happy Reformation, and a pure Doctryne, be greived to parte with a little? In the ſecond of Chronicles, chap. 31, 8, we reade thus: <hi>And when Hezekiah and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces came and ſawe the heapes, they bleſsed the Lord, and his people Iſraell.</hi> So likewiſe, 2. Cor. 9, 12, the Apoſtle ſaith thus: <hi>The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of this Service, not onely ſupplieth the neceſsities of the Saincts, but alſo is aboundant by the Thankſgivinge of many unto God.</hi> And, Phili pp. 4, 17, he ſaith: <hi>Not that I deſire a Gift but I deſire the fruict which may further your reckoninge. Now I have received all: and have plenty: I was even filled, after that I had received of Epaphroditus that which came from you, an odour that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150735:26"/>ſmelleth ſweete, a ſacrifice acceptable and pleaſant to God.</hi> Here we ſee what Bleſſings, what Thankſgivinge to God, this libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality in Gods people towards the Lords Miniſters, ſtirred up in the Kinges and Apoſtles of the Church, here we ſee alſo that this is to God as a Sacrifice acceptable, and pleaſinge unto him. And our Lord himſelfe, Math. 10, 42, ſaith thus: <hi>Whoſoever ſhall give unto one of theiſe little ones to drinke a Cup of cold Water onely, in the Name of a Diſciple, verely I ſay unto you, he ſhall not loſe his rewarde.</hi> It is a pretious thinge therefore in the ſight of God, when any one giveth to his Miniſters, becauſe they are his Miniſters, and giveth not onely of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity or of Superfluity; for we muſt not give, onely becauſe of our Superfluity we cann give; but we ought to give in faith, ſayinge in our hearts: Lord, this is a Miniſter of thy Church, I give therefore to him, Beleevinge thy vvorde of Acceptance. This is a holy Liberality: this true Chriſtian Liberality, therefore thus mynded, (and not grudgingely, or onely for the Lawes ſake) we ſhould give to the Maintenance of the Lords Miniſters. For this cauſe as I have vvritten for our Biſhopps and Arch-Biſhopps, ſo I write alſo for our Parriſh Cleargy, that the full Tythes be allovved, and that Peoples free will Offeringes may be admitted, untill each Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh throughout the Land, have a competent Meanes for the Cleargy of the ſame. How bounrifull were our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors in givinge of Lands for a certainety of Revenewe, to frieries and Nunneries? if then they were ſo bountifull where God impoſed no bond ſo to doe, and this upon them who proved unproffitable Members of the Church, ſhould not we much more give ſome parte of our Lands, for a certainety of maintenance to the needefull Cleargy of our Pariſhes! If therefore any Pariſhes be ſo ſmale, or poore, that it yeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not a competent Meanes for the Cleargy thereof, it would be a bleſſed thinge, if thoſe that are able, give ſome
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150735:26"/>parte of their Lande, to yeild to the ſame a certainety of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venewe, beſides the Tithes, and other Benefits which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh its ſelfe yeildeth. The needefull Cleargy of a Parriſh I accoumpt, a Paſtor or Teacher, and a Deacon for an aſſiſtant unto him; for truly it is not meete, that we put him to read Divine Service alwayes, and alwayes to doe other Cleargi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Dutyes, who ſhould give himſelfe diligently to Reading, that he may Preach the Ghoſpell often unto us, and ſoundly. If therefore in Pariſhes already ſufficiently provided for, there be any ſo Chriſtianly mynded, as that of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of their poſſeſſions they will ſet by a parte, towards the Maintenance of the Cleargy of another Parriſh which hath neede, I humbly petition your Majeſtie that you gratiouſly permit this. To theiſe I may add the Maintayninge of ſuch Officers alſo, as are neceſſary for the perfourmance of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne and Divine Service in our Cathedralls: and alſo ſuch as neceſſarily neede in our Schooles and Univerſities; for if God ſo gratiouſly accepted, 1. Chron. 17, 1, of the augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the State and Magnificence of his vvorſhipp, which vve fynde after the Buildinge of the Temple, then may we under the Chriſtianity alſo Beleeve, that our Princes caringe to increaſe in a tyme of the Churches proſperity, the State &amp; Magnificence of the vvorſhipp of God, is moſt acceptable to God, and conſequently the Officers neceſſary in ſuch Service may, (though not all as Cleargy) be maintayned of the Charte of Gods people. And ſo likewiſe, becauſe the churches ſupply with learned &amp; able Miniſters is ſight needful, therfore as our Schooles or Univerſities are needefull, for the trayning up of ſome hereunto, ſo the Governours of them are alſo needefull, as doinge for Gods Church a very ſpeciall Service; therefore alſo ſuch are to be Maintayned at the Charge of Gods people, that ſo they may be incouraged in the Service of the Lord. But one thing here I wiſh and petition for, that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150735:27"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:150735:27"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:150735:28"/>ſuch be the large Revenewe of every ſeverall Eccleſiaſticall Officer of our Cleargy, as that the Meanes of the livinge being ſufficient, no one of them be ſuffered to ingroſs any more ſpirituall livings into his hande: for it is the villifyinge and decayinge alſo the Miniſtration of the Ghoſpell, when one Man havinge divers Charges, executes one himſelfe, and leaves the reſt, either unto too ſeldome viſitation, or elſe to ſome readinge and inſufficient Miniſter.</p>
                  <p>Thus having written for the Maintenance of our Miniſters, I wil proceede to write alſo of the Repairing of our churches.</p>
                  <p>If the Lord ſo gratiouſly accepted, of the diſpoſition of Kinge David, concerninge increaſinge the Magnificenſe of the vvorſhipp of God, 1. Chron. 17, 3, by changinge the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle into a glorious and magnificent Temple, why ſhould we not thinke that under the Chriſtianity alſo, the Lord moſt gratiouſly regardeth our beautifyinge of the very Temples where he is vvorſhipped? how ill befitting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it, that in this lands, but ſpecially in our country Pariſhes, Gods Temples are moſt baſely provided for, lyinge ſo ruined, and ſo duſty, as that it cannot but abate the devotion of Gods people. My humble petition is therefore unto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, that you provinge an engliſh Ioſiah, zealous of the glory and ſplendour of Gods Temples, permit the free will Offeringes of your people, untill there be ſufficient for the Repayringe and Adorninge of the Churches of God. It is truly an error in ſome under the Reformation, that they (ſo as they but vvorſhipp God in his Temple) make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of Beautifyinge and Enrichinge alſo the place of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblinge; but now from the Example of the Church under the Lawe we ſee, how acceptable to God the Care and Bounty of Gods Kinges and People is, even in this matter of Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyinge the very Churches wherein we vvorſhipp God. As for the manner of Adorninge of Churches, though ſome
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150735:28"/>like Pictures of holy Stories, yet I rather wiſh a pain tinge &amp; guildinge, as the Arches, and faſhion of pillars, wil beſt agree with, and a wrytinge of Divine Stories here and there. For truly I fynde the Lord, no where to commend to his people any former things done, to be repreſented by Pictures; but rather he commends unto them a writinge of his vvorde about their howſes, and in memoriall of things paſſed, to ſet up either Stones, or other like things, which carry no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the thinge done, This I take to be to the end, that for matters of faith, which vve muſt have faith of that once it vvas done, he vvould not uſe us to any repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame to our eye. And indeede what this Deviſe of picturinge Divine Stories in Churches came unto under Popery, vve may mourningely perceave; for the next to this was Images alſo, and then Idolatry. Men are too proane to delight to be put in mynde of things of faith, by pictures of the ſame ſet before their eye; but it is the next way to put faith out of the hearte, and argues a falle in wardly of the ſight of thoſe things, by faith of the vvorde reade and Preached. For theiſe cauſes (Dread Soveraigne) I humbly petion, that your people be not accouſtomed againe as under Popery, to Pictures of things of the Divine Story; but rather that they may learne to have a ſight, through faith of the vvorde prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and reade, &amp; ſo adorne the Churches rather with ſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paintinges and guildinges, then with paintinge of Stories. Moreover, becauſe in ſome places the Congregation is ſo greate, and the Church either ſo ſcante, or ſo ill provided of roome, that the people ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not conveniently kneele at praier, or ſit the tyme of the Sermon, meete it is that ſuch Churches be either in larged, or provided of Galleries and formes, as neede requireth; for it is no ſmale diſorder, when a Church is glorious by Adorninges, and yet not fitted for the peoples worſhipp. Laſtly, whereas our Church (in the ordinary Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150735:29"/>hath well ordered, a ſettinge aparte one parte of the Church for Men, another for Women, ſo preventinge a dangerous intermixture of the Sexes in that place, I humbly petition, that the diſorder hereof in ſome populous Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations may be redreſſed.</p>
                  <p>If therefore at any populous Aſſembly it fall out, that there be diſorder herein, meete it is that the Governours have power of the Seates, to diſpoſe them to Men, &amp; Women a parte by themſelvs; neither truly is there in theiſe tymes little neede of this, if the vvickedneſs of ſome in populous Congregations were knowen. To avoide therefore an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and advantage of evell, it is very neeedefull to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve more ſtrictly then now uſually is done, that cuſtome of our Church, in orderinge one parte of the Church for Men, the other for Women.</p>
                  <p>Thus havinge written alſo of the Repayringe and Ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of Churches, I humbly pray, that I may proceede to the laſt obſervation made upon the former collected Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which was, That when there was a Sufficiency, this was to be acknowledged by the Cleargy, and the people to be ſtaied from Offeringe.</p>
                  <p>It hath bene an old fault in the Cleargy, but ſpecially un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Popery, never to acknowledge a Sufficiency of Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but to be ever cryinge, Give, Give, and this to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable burtheninge of Gods people. And which worſe is, there hath bene a multiplyinge of the Orders of Cleargy, above that which in old tymes was: and alſo an increaſe of Offices, rather for the Service of the Romane Papacyes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull extent of Iuriſdiction, then for the neceſſary Service of the Ghoſpell, and of the worſhipp of God. Neither have wicked Men reſted vvith this, but they have added, the ſwarminge of religious Orders of friers and Nunnes, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge them (all that may be) to exhauſt Threaſure from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150735:29"/>Gods people. Therefore when a Lande is well divided in to Pariſhes, Biſhopdomes, and Arch-Biſhopdomes, and when the Cathedrall Churches, and Schooles, are of conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Number, fit it is, that theiſe havinge ſufficient Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, it may be to the glory of God acknowledged, and all unneceſſary burthenings of Gods people removed. And truly it is a wonder to ſee the corruption of things, in that the falſe Cleargy, and the Offices ſervinge rather the Antichriſtian uſurpation, then the Miniſtration of the Ghoſpell, and the unlawfull orders of Friers and Nunnes, exhauſt farr more of the Threaſure of Gods people, then doth the true and neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Cleargy ordeined by God. As for falſe Orders of Cleargy, me thinkes the very evidence of their addition, to the Orders of Cleargy in the primitive tymes, ſhould move men to perceave and hate the Corruption. And as for thoſe Offices which ſerve the Pope rather then the Ghoſpell, me thinkes that the evidence of the evell of the Popes extent of Iuriſdiction, ſhould move the Nations to put of from them the burthen of all ſuch Offices. And for Prieries and Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neries, ſeinge the Ghoſpell warrants not, that every one that will but give himſelfe to Praier, ſhould preſently charge the Church of God; but rather ordeynes, <hi>that all eate their owne Bread,</hi> 2. Theſſal. 3, 10, except Gods Cleargy, even they who Miniſter the Ghoſpel, 1. Cor. 9, 6; therefore me thinkes, that as the Nations would not be guilty, of maintayninge ſuch as live inordinately, and this to the expreſs diſobeyinge of a very ſpeciall Ordinance of God, ſo they ſhould not ſuffer among them the ſwarminge of Friers and Nunnes, who all live of other, not of their owne labour or Meanes. True it is, that it hath bene an Ornament to the Church, yea and to the Ghoſpell, that ſome ſingle Perſons have given up themſelvs to ſerve God extraordinarily in Praiers and Supplications, and to be ſerviceable in Chriſtian Dutyes to ſuch as had Neede,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150735:30"/>yea and to live ſingle and chaſte; but though vve under the Reformation alſo, may doe well to honor ſuch in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, yet let us not bynde them by Profeſſion or vowe ever to continue ſo, but rather commend them to Gods Grace to continue or diſcontinue as God ſhall move and inable them. And much leſs let us ſuffer ſuch to live inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately, by livinge upon that taken from others, but rather let them live of their owne Meanes, or elſe apply themſelvs to worke. It is evell lookinge upon the Showe onely of Devotion, when vvithall, diſobediences to Gods holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, are ſuffered in them who make ſuch Showe.</p>
                  <p>To conclude therefore, I now humbly petition your ſacred Majeſtie, that a Sufficiency beinge provided, for the true Cleargy of Pariſhes, and for Biſhops and Arch-Biſhops, &amp; ſuch Cleargy as neceſſarily neede in Offices under them: as alſo for our Cathedrall churches ſolemne Divine Service, and for our Schooles and Univerſities: And laſtly, when our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and Cathedrall churches are ſufficiently provided of Adornements, aſwell of the Temple, as of Miniſteriall veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; then that People be ſtaied from Offeringe any more unto the vvorke, ſave onely as new Repayringe of thinges ſhall renewe occaſion.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe experience hath declared, that the Cleargy beinge once ſufficiently provided for, and made ſure of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyinge duringe life ſuch Maintenance, have growen laſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious of life, light of Geſture, yea and negligent of Preaching the Ghoſpell conveniently often, therefore I humbly peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a prevention, of this abuſe of yours and your Peoples Bounty. This prevention is no otherwiſe to be done, then by ſubiectinge our Cleargy to danger, in caſe that upon being ſetled in a livinge, they then behave not themſelvs as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the Miniſters of the Ghoſpell. Our Church at hir givinge Orders hath taken Care hereof in hir Charge
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150735:30"/>given to them who are Ordeined, and in takinge of them a Rynde of Promiſe ſo to doe; but the faile is, that afterwards they not doinge ſo, the Reporte of the Pariſhioners is not hearkened unto, unleſs ſome formall Accuſation ſecond the ſame. Under this Sheild our Cleargy are ſo carcleſs to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Showe of Godlineſs and Holineſs, that rather they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to the contrary, even to a Showe of licentious Liberty. Truly when I ſawe the very Showe of Sanctity which Popiſh Preiſts make, and marked the effect and power even thereof in the people, I wiſhed the true Sanctity of ſome of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in them, &amp; their Showe of Sanctity in all our Divines: for the very Showe of Devotion and Sanctity in Preiſts, as it anſwereth to the holy Offices they hold, and profeſſion they make, ſo it is not in vaine to the people of God, but rather is a Light and example unto them. For this cauſe I here peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the voice of the Pariſhioners concerninge their Cleargy may be hearkened after, as a Meanes to come to the knowledge of the lightneſs, or evell Manners of their Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: For Men are loath to be Accuſers in Courts of Iuſtice, when yet in faithfulneſs, and with true Charity towards Gods Church, they cann ſee, and ſeinge mourne for, the Lightneſs, laſciviouſneſs, Looſeneſs, and evell diſpoſition and Manners of their Cleargy.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, it were good, that our Biſhops bounde our Divines, to the uſinge of religious exerciſes &amp; dutyes in their familyes, ſuch as are Morninge and Eveninge Praier, Grace before and after Meare, Readinge the Scriptures by them of their houſehold by turnes, Repetition of Sermons, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſinge conveniently often; for hardly cann a Man ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in his family theiſe things, but it will bynde him to have a care of his owne Manners and Converſation, that it be not in his family, nor abroade in Company, otherwiſe then Godly and Religious. We have ſeene the lamentable
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150735:31"/>effects of Riches and Glory in the Cleargy, when Gods Princes and People havinge given bountifully unto them, and made ſuch Bounty aſſured alſo unto them to injoy the ſame: for then the Cleargy have taken Liberty, to live li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſly, and ungodly. Neither cann we expect any other fruict of greate Revenews in Cleargy-Men, if Gods Princes awe them not with the Sworde, profeſſinge the uſe of the ſame againſt them, if they leave to be that which God by his vvorde requires them to be, and be that which Gods vvorde condemnes. Let us enrich our Cleargy, but let us not hurte them, either by an exceſs in Giving, or by leavinge the reines of their Manners wholy unto themſelvs. How greate hurte did thoſe two greate Emperors doe to the Cleargy, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the greate, and Charles the greate, if the reporte of their Donations to the Biſhop of Rome be true? vvhat Blood have thoſe Lands occaſioned the ſheddinge of? what bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have thoſe poſſeſſions ingendred in the Cleargy of that city? By thoſe poſſeſſions cheifly, the Cleargy of that city grew not onely licentious, but alſo incorrigible; but it hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth both the Cleargy and alſo the Church of God, when Gods Princes poſſeſs the Cleargy of ſuch meaſure of poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as that both they will be wicked, and alſo are able to reſiſt the Diſcipline of the Sworde, if any Prince would in duty to God make uſe of it againſt them. Therefore of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer experience we of theiſe tymes may beware, that we poſſeſs not the Cleargy of too large and indeede Superfluous Revenews, leaſt they growe the cleane contrary to that which the vvorde of God requires them to be. Yea to come neerer home, doe but looke upon our ſilken Cleargy ſince they have but felt the blaſt of the Princes favour, obſerve their lightneſs of Geſture, boldneſs againſt all Men, liberty in ſpeach, that I add not, laſſiviouſneſs and luſſfull vvanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I ſpeake of our yonger ſorte of Cleargy, who by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150735:31"/>are apteſt, and therefore firſt doe beginn a declination from Cleargicall Holineſs; but, have no eye at theiſe to marke and correct their abuſe of this Grace, and ſhortly, even when they grow older to ſupply the roomes of our Biſhops, you ſhall have a new a wicked Bpiſcopacy. Therefore I humbly pray your ſacred Majeſſie, not that you change from favouriuge, honoringe, and enriching our Cleargy, but onely that an eye may be had of them that they abuſe not this Grace, turning it into ungodly liberty: As alſo, that our clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy be enjoyned to uſe their family to religious houſehold dutyes: and laſtly, that the reporte or ſame of thoſe who are converſant or neighbours with our Cleargy, may be hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after by our Biſhops, and occaſion thereby taken, to have an eye at ſuch, whoſe light behayiour, looſeneſs of converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, lewdneſs of life, or neglect of holy family exerciſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares their corruption though the ſetled and tich livinges they enjoy.</p>
                  <p>If this be taken heede unto by our Biſhopps: if alſo your Majeſtie vouchſafe to be zealous herein, givinge alſo Power to your Miniſters of your Kingedome to have a care of, &amp; an eye at theiſe things in the Cleargy neere them, then would I not ſeare any harme, by the moderate increaſe of your and your Peoples Bounty towards our Cleargy. With the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioninge vvhereof, I cloſe up this Chapter alſo, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede to an other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:150735:32"/>
                  <head>III. CHAP. <hi>OF Kinge leheſhaphat we reade a, Chron, 17, 7: That he ſent his Princes, and with them Levits and Preists, who taught in the Cityes of Iudah, and had the booke of the Lawe of the Lord with them, and went about throughout all the Cityes of Iudnb, and taught the People.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>From this Scripture I obſerve, That the Kinge did not onely take Care that there were Teachers, but alſo that thoſe Teachers teach the Peoplet yea he joyned his Princes in this Care, that in every City they ſhould ſee, that the People be taught by their Teachers. I therefore obſervinge in this Kingedome, that many-many Pariſhes, either had no Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, or having Teachers, yet thoſe Teachers careleſsly taught the People, Preachinge the Ghoſpell once a month onely for ſatisfyinge the Lawe, was moved to write that my ſhorte and Zealous little vvrytinge, which firſt I exhibited to your facred hands at Theobalds; adventuringe now alſo, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue my petition in this vvritinge more at large. Neither would I have troubled your Majeſtie with this petition, if it were not evident to all Men, that neither leangth of tyme, nor crye of people, have prevayled over our Teachers to teach their People diligently. Neither have our Biſhops furniſhed each Parriſh with a Teachinge Miniſter, neither have they puniſhed thoſe, who cann teach, but doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently often Preach unto the People. If your Majeſtie therefore, and your Princes aſſiſt them, that they may place Teachers where there are none, and may puniſh or remove ſuch as can teach, but doe not, or if at all, yet not conveniently often, you ſhall doe a holy vvork, &amp; ſhall greatly benefit the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150735:32"/>Church of God. Your Majeſtie hath good experience (bleſſed be God) but that out Univerſities are not ſo barren as not to affoorde Teachers enough, &amp; alſo that your people are not ſo ſparing, as not to give largely (beſides what of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity they give) to have a Teacher appointed uuto them; for many are the places in this Kingedome, vvhere beinge ill fitted with thoſe ſetled in the livings, they of their voluntary raiſe from amonge them a yearely ſtipend for a hired Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. Seinge therefore Gods bleſſinge is ſuch upon our Univerſities: ſeing alſo your people are ſo well diſpoſed, pitty it vvere to force them to content themſelvs with a dumbe Preiſt ſo longe as he liveth. My petition therefore unto your Majeſtie is, that where one poſſeſſeth the place who cannot Preach, and where any one poſſeſſeth the place, who though he cann, yet doth not conveniently often Preach unto the people, there ſuch be removed from the livinge, havinge onely ſome ſmale yearily ſtipend allowed them, &amp; an other placed in the ſame, who both cann and will Preach the vvorde conveniently often. Surely if ſuch were awed with hazard of the livinge, who though they cann, yet doe not preach conveniently often, this woulde provoake them to ſtudy harder, and with practiſe to attaine a ſacility in Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge, that ſo they may conveniently often Preach the vvorde: for, vve ſee how carefull they are of all thoſe things, by which they ſhall hazard the loſs of their livinge. And is not Teachinge the very ſpeciall Duty of a Teacher vvhat therefore ſhould rather hazard the loſs of his livinge then a Negligent Teachinge? If it be now demanded, what I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpt conveniently often, I anſwere, once upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth day, if not twice; for uuly, Monthly Sermons ſerve not, cither for the ſufficient inſtructinge of people in the Divine Myſteries, or for the reprooſe of their evellManners. Alas (my Lord) if the vvorde preached be appointed for a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150735:33"/>Soule-food, cann the Soules of Men be fed with Monthly Sermons? but your Majeſtie is not ignorant, that in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-Pariſhes, ſuch is the backwardneſs of people to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande and conceave the Myſteries of religion neceſſary to Silvation: ſuch alſo, not the rudeneſs onely, but the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of diſpoſition concerninge Manners, that it muſt be no ſmale labour to inſtruct them in the one, and to Reforme them by Religion in the other. Teachinge is not barely the leavinge a Sermon with a company of people, but it is the fittinge the vvorde to the preſent Neceſſityes of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; therefore alſo he that will be a good Paſtor or Teacher, muſt have his eyes and cares abroade amonge his Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to obſerve what they are ignorant in, &amp; what erronious opinions any fall into, and what their life and converſation uſually is, and whither in their familyes they uſe or neglect religious dutyes, for, who ſo doth not this, as he cannot well knowe the Neceſſityes of his Pariſhioners, ſo alſo he knowes not to fit the vvorde to the occaſions. But becauſe, cither the antient may be ignorant in ſome points of Religion very neceſſary to their Salvation: or becauſe the ignorant youth growes dayly in each Parriſh or becauſe they vvhich knowe religious Myſteries neede incouragement and confirmation in them: or becauſe Satans temptations, and the corruption of Manners is never idle, but dally aſſaults the people, to drawe them either to neglect the worde, or not to obey and obſerve it in their life and converſation, therfore there is neceſſity of Preachinge the vvorde once at the leaſt every Sabbaoth, and Monthly Sermons ſuffiſe not. That kynde of Preachinge vvhich takes a text at random, and onely in largeth a diſcours as it gives occaſion, is but a kinde of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Preachinge, vvhich may fit all places; but Paſtorall Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge needeth a reſpect to the occaſions of the Parriſh. Vaine vvere phiſick if it reſted onely with a generall decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150735:33"/>what is good for ſuch and ſuch diſeaſes, and did not moreover deſcend to perticuler diſeaſed Perſons, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied as the Neceſſityes require; even ſo is it alſo vvith Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Who vvould coumpt him a good Shepheard, who though he knowes and cann declare all diſeaſes, &amp; all reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies pertayninge to Sheepe, yet applies not each remedy as any diſeaſed Sheeps gives occaſion? It is therefore a defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Teachinge, where either the Paſtor is ignorant of the ſpirituall diſeaſes of his people, or knowinge them, yet fits not the vvorde of God unto them, or havinge onely done that, leaves to ſecond the Preachinge, with the Power and Diſcipline of Rule and Goverment. Alas, how ſmale effects of the vvorde preached fynde we, vvhere the Paſtor havinge Taught his people, hath no Power nor Authority further, to judge and puniſh the diſobedient.</p>
                  <p>And indeede what other fruict or ſucceſs cann we expect, while we ſever that which God joyned togeather? for he joyned eccleſiaſticall Power of ludgement and Puniſhment with the miniſtration of the worde. Let us but looke into ſeverall Pariſhes, where ludgement &amp; Puniſhment doe not accompany the worde preached, but the Paſtor reſts vvith his leavinge a Sermon onely, and the people are left for matter of Goverment or Rule to the Biſhops Courte, and there let us obſerve, if the people be not ſo careleſs of the vvorde once hearde, that they care not of all the vvecke after, either to thinke any more of it, or to reforme themſelvs in any one thinge by it. Hence partly it is, that where there is every Sabbaoth day Teachinge, yet the People remaine as unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly in their converſation, as if they never heard the word of God at all; though indeede in ſome few places, the earneſt zeale of the Preacher, prevailes over the people to take the more heede, &amp; the more conſcionably to obſerve the things Preached; but yet even there it is evident, what a defect there
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150735:34"/>is of Rule to accompany the Preachinge. Neither let us thinke that the Churches Rule and Diſcipline, ſhould not ſtreatch unto the very converſation or ſpeach of Men, ſeinge the Ghoſpell reſts not with actions onely, but ſtreatcheth its ſeife unto Mens Speaches alſo; therefore vve reade, Epheſ. 4, 29: Let no corrupt communication proceede out of your mouths: and verſe, 31: Let all evell ſpeakinge be put avvay from you. And chap. 5, 3: All uncleaneſs, let it not be once named among you, neither filthineſs, neither fooliſh talking, neither jeſtinge, which are thinges not comely.</p>
                  <p>Theiſe and many the like precepts the Ghoſpell gives to Men even concerninge Speach, neither are theiſe to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpted as bare Counſailes, but rather as Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which the Diſcipline of the Church ſhould correct in the diſobedient. True it is, that the Ghoſpell ſtreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth alſo to the affections, yea to the very thoughts of Men, when yet the Churches Diſcipline cannot ſtreatch to ſuch things alſo; but yet becauſe Diſcipline is ordeyned for things that come fourth of Men, therefore it ought to ſecond aſwel the Precepts concerninge Speach, as the precepts concerning Actions of Drunkenneſs, Fornication, Adultery, Theft, or Idolatry. Though the Lawes of Kingedomes therefore, ſtreatch not to filthy ſpeakinge, to puniſh it vvhere it is uſuall, yet the Churches Diſcipline ought to ſtreatch even to it.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore (Dread Soveraigne) I now humbly pray, that ſuch Teachers may be appointed Paſtors of our Parriſh churches, as who not onely reprove corrupt Communication by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge, but alſo Rulinge according to the Doctryne Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, doe take notice of unchriſtian Communication in their Pariſhioners, joyninge vvith the Rulinge Elders of the Parriſh, both in callinge ſuch to Accoumpt, and in judginge the ſame, and puniſhinge ſuch as continue ſtill in that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150735:34"/>not with ſtandinge any exhortation or warninge given. This is truly to feede the flock: this is truly to Teach; therefore if your Princes by commiſſion from you, doe in their ſeverall abidinges or dwellinges, obſerve in the Cleargy the Neglect hereof, and leave it not to the Biſhop onely to call ſuch Cleargy to accoumpt, but doe themſelvs (the Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop not proceedinge after ſufficient Notice, againſt ſuch Cleargy) proceede againſt them, executinge as your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters your Power in the reprovinge and puniſhinge of ſuch, then would the Cleargy of our Land be awed, &amp; your people would ſurely be diligently and proffitably Taught. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I petition your Majeſtie, that the Care hereof be not left to our Biſhops and Cleargy onely, but that your Princes, Iuſtices, and other Magiſtrates, may in places remote from your Princely preſence, have alſo authority to ſee to the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge of the People, and to the Cleargyes executing, both concerninge Teachinge alſo &amp; Rule, their true Dutyes &amp; Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in every of our Pariſh Churches.</p>
                  <p>Thus havinge vvritten hereof alſo, I humbly pray that I may proceede, to vvrite of other things in another Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:150735:35"/>
                  <head>IV. CHAP. <hi>OF King Hezekiah we reade, 2, Chron, 29, 27: That he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to offer the burnt Offerings upon the Altar: And when the Offerings begann, the ſonge of the Lord begann with the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, &amp; the Inſtruments of David Kinge of Iſraell. And all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation worſhipped, ſinginge a ſonge, and they blew the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pcts: All this continued untill the burnte offeringe was finiſhed. And when they had made an end of Offeringe, the Kinge, and all that were preſent with him, bowed themſelvs, &amp; worſhipped. Then Hezekiah the Kinge, and the Princes, commanded the Levits to praiſe the Lord with the wordes of David, and of Aſaph the Seer. And Hezekiah ſpake, and ſaid, Now ye have conſecrate your ſelvs, come neere, and bringe the ſacrifices, and offering of praiſe, into the houſe of the Lord. Alſo, Hezektah ſent to all Iſraell and Indah, and alſo wrote letters to Ephraim, and Manaſſeh, that they ſhould come to the houſe of the Lord in Hieruſalem, to keepe the Paſſeover unto the Lord God of Iſraell. And Hezekiah ſpake comfortably unto all the Levits, that had knowledge to ſinge unto the Lord.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>From theiſe Scriptures I gather ſpecially theiſe fower thinges: 1: That in tyme of peace and proſperity, the Lords vvorſhip may be increaſed in Magnificenſe: 2: That the King tooke care, of the ſolemne, Stately, and right perfourmance of the ſame: 3: That thoſe vvho have the Arte in ſonge, and in Muſick, vvere cheriſ hed by the Kinge: 4: That the Kinge tooke care of, and ſurthered, the Peoples reſorte unto the ſame.</p>
                  <p>It is truly vvorthy our obſervation, that unto the Manner of Divine Service ordeyned in the vvilderneſs, God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150735:35"/>of the Additions of Kinges and Prophets, made in lymes vvhen the Church vvas in Peace and Proſperity: For here vve reade of the vvords of David, and Aſaph the Secr: alſo, of the Inſtruments of David Kinge of Iſraell; neither of which lived in the tyme when the Church was in the vvilderneſſe. If therefore God approved of this Addition, vvhich made in ſome meaſure a change of the former Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Divine Service, why ſhould we under the Chriſtianity thinke, that the increaſe of the Magnificence of the vvorſhip of God is not acceptable? They are therefore to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, who contend againſt the Magniſicent Manner of Divine Service, ordeyned by Gods Kinges and Preiſts, and not diſſonant from his former reveiled will, vvhich we fynde eſtabliſhed in the Chriſtian Church, after the Kinges and Princes embraced the Chriſtian faith. Neither ought any to thinke, that Kinges being converted to God, they have not a ſpeciall prerogative in orderinge the ſet forme of Divine Service.</p>
                  <p>I graunte, they are not left wholy at Liberty to doe what pleaſerrh them; for I noted before in the firſt chapter, that the Comandement vvas by the hande of the Lord, and by the hande of his Prophets; but yet this I ſay, that under the Chriſtianity, where we have not new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations for all things, there the Kinge and Gods Preiſts have power, to order the Manner of the Divine vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp, ſo as they doe nothinge in Subſtance againſt the vvill of God already reveiled. They may indeede under the ſheild of this liberty, bringe in many vaine and nnſeemely thinges; but vve truſt to Gods ſtronge hande over them.</p>
                  <p>And if they be ſo ill mynded, yet vvee neede not doubt, but that the Lorde vvill in due tyme diſcover their evell, and raiſe up redreſs for his CHVRCH,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150735:36"/>by the hands of more faithfull Servants. In the meane tyme, if they commande things, which in themſelvs are not againſt the vvorde of God reveiled, we are ſafer in obeyinge, then reſiſtinge. I approve not therefore of thoſe, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſely ſpeake of the ſolemne Service of our Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Churches, ſpeakinge rather their owne ſingular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, then that which hath any ſounde warrant from the vvorde of God.</p>
                  <p>Theiſe things conſidered, I now for this matter conclude, That God is to be bleſſed, for your Majeſties Iudgement and vviſedome, in retayninge ſtill under the Reformation, the Magnificent Manner of Gods Divine vvorſhipp uſed in our Cathedrall churches, and in ſome few other places; for, ſeinge the ſame was ordered by former Princes and Biſhops, it was fit to be retayned, ſave onely vvherein vve have direct vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by the vvorde of God, or by evidence of evell, to alter &amp; Reforme the ſame: for vve owe a Reverence to that vvhich former Miniſters of God have ordered, ſave in things which either are directly againſt Gods vvorde, or which carry vvith them an evidence of evell. But now, as on the one hande I bleſſe God, for your Majeſties continuinge the Stately vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in our Cathedrall Churches, ſo on the other hande I humbly pray, that I may make two petitions: the firſt, That the peoples underſtandinges may be more yet ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered then hitherto it hàth bene: the ſecond: That the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge Men, and others imploied in any Service, may be taken care of, that they be of an honeſt, religious, and holy life and Converſation.</p>
                  <p>For the better perfourmance of the firſt, it vvere good and proffitable, That vvhatſoever is ſunge or plaide in that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Divine Service, be printed in bookes, that the ſame may be read by the people, at the tyme of the ſinginge or playinge the ſame in the Quire. Neither this onely, but it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150735:36"/>vvere alſo good that the people were inſtructed, both readily to knowe vvhat is ſunge or plaide, and alſo readily to turne to the ſame in the booke vvhere they may reade it: yea, children ſhould be taught this in the Schooles; that ſo beinge trained up hérein, they may in their age reſorte proffitably to this ſolemne Service alſo ſometymes, aſwell as to their ovvne Parriſh Church ordinarily. For, (Dread Soveraigne) though charitably and religiouſly, your Predeceſſors have cauſed the Divine Service to be tranſlated into the Engliſh tongue, yet, partly, becauſe al that aſſemble, cannot conveniëtly aſſemble in the Quire, (neither cann the Quire be altered, becauſe of the fittinge the ſame to the voices of the Singers, that they may heare one an other): partly, becauſe Songe cannot be ſo diſtinct, as that the hearers can farr off diſcerne what is ſung: partly, becauſe the Muſick plaieth ſome tymes alone in the Honour of God, vvhen yet ſome thinge is, or ought to be intended, the tune whereof is with Arte of Muſick plaide al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one: and laſtly, becauſe the common ſorte are not ſkilfull in the Order, what is now ſunge, what then plaide; therefore, your people are even in theiſe tymes little better, then if the Service were perfourmed in a ſtrange tongue. Herethrough cheifely it is, that your people doe not commonly ſo reſpect that ſolemne Service as they ought, neither indeede care at all to reſorte to the ſame at any tyme; yea, and moſt of thoſe that doe ſometymes come to the ſame, come neere onely vvhen ſome thinge is read out of the Bible, or when thoſe Praiers are ſaid, which eaſily they cann diſcerne and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande; but when any thinge is done in Songe, or vvhen the Muſick ſilently plaieth, you ſhall then ſynde them to retire themſelvs, and to give themſelvs to vvalkinge and talkinge. Others, of the yet ſimpler ſorte of people, are (even as thoſe under Popery) pleaſed vvith the tune onely, and delighted with the ſonge and Muſick, and vvith the ſight of the Stately
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150735:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:150735:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:150735:38"/>ordetinge and perfourmance of things; but this, without ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe at any tyme to vvorſhipp God in the Spirit, and vvith the underſtandinge, ſo that they onely ſtand gazinge, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge it a ſufficient worſhipp if they have but bene there, &amp; ſeene Divine Service. But as this evell in Gods people cannot but be diſpleaſinge to God, ſo ſurely if ſome good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be not taken for redreſs hereof, it cannot but endanger the Lords acceptance of the very Service its ſelfe: for, it is not ſo much the Service vvherein a few vvorſhip, as the vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of many in Spirit that he regards.</p>
                  <p>Thus havinge vvritten of my firſt petition, I humbly pray, that I may proceede to the ſecond,</p>
                  <p>If onely Art be heeded in them admitted Miniſters in the Divine Service, as if (ſo they be ſkillfull, then) it matters not what their lives and converſations be, then vvhen any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane or irreligiouſly diſpoſed Perſons are admitted, we (from experience) cann hardly expect other, then that their unſanctified Soules will bringe fourth, as prophaneſs in their life and converſation abroade, ſo irreverence and a meaſure of prophaneſs in the very execution of their parts in the Divine vvorſhipp. But when people ſee irreverence, or any meaſure prophaneſs in the Miniſters, it abates their devotion, and is no ſmale Scandall to the Service its ſelfe. Therefore I humbly petition, that our Biſhops have not care that they reverently perfourme their parts in the Service onely, but alſo that they or the Deanes doe inquire of their life and converſation abroade alſo out of the Church: for, if abroade in their howſes, or common company, they be wanton, laſcivious or prophane, no Awe will ſerve to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreine, that in the Service alſo their diſpoſition breake not fourth upon every little advantage or opportunity to ſhew the ſame. If therefore our Biſhopps and Deanes Inquire after the common life and converſation of ſuch what it is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150735:38"/>abroade out of the Church: if alſo they inquire whither in their familyes they uſe or neglect religious Dutyes, ſuch as are eveninge Praier at leaſtwiſe, Grace before &amp; after meate, readinge the Divine Scriptures, Repeatinge of Sermons ſome tymes, and ſome tymes Chatechiſinge; then this would Awe them to exerciſe themſelvs to a Holineſs of life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; Eſpecially, if as they ſhall be founde conformable, or diſorderly, ſo they ſhall be admitted, or put by the Service. Yea it were good, that an exhortation were given to all, that if any of them knowe any amonge them, to be looſe and laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civious of Speach, prophane in converſation, or negligent of religious Dutyes in their familyes, they ſhould informe the Biſhop or Deane of the ſame, that ſo the party may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, &amp; as occaſion is given be proceeded againſt. Verily, it greately endangers the Service, both towards God, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men, when the Miniſters of the ſame are knowen, to be wicked Men in their life and converſation: for it cannot be but that the Lord ſhould turne his face, even from a good Service executed by ſuch, (if authority allowe ſuch to be Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters therein, as who commonly are knowen to be wicked of life and converſation): Neither cann it be but that the people alſo, ſhould take ſuch offence at ſuch, as that even the very Service alſo ſhall well neere be ſorſaken.</p>
                  <p>If theiſe things therefore (Dread Soveraigne) be carefully ſeene unto, I nothinge doubt, but that our Divine Servico now uſed in our Cathedrall Churches, will both be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God then heretofore, and alſo more conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and religiouſly then heretoſote ſrequented by your people. I may here add the like petition againſt our Clearkes of Pariſhes, who commonly beinge of the lewdeſt of the Partiſh for life and converſation, doe alſo ſo irreverently, unſkilfully, and unſeemely perfourme their Office, that the people of God cannot but take offence there
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150735:39"/>at, and this to the ſcandall of the Service its ſelfe of out Church.</p>
                  <p>To conclude my Collections, together with my obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s upon theiſe collected Scriptures, I now humbly petition, that as here it is ſaid, That the Kinge, and the Princes comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp;c: ſo as in your Preſence your ſelfe ſee to theiſe things, ſo likewiſe in places remote from your ſacred Preſence, your Princes and Magiſtrats (by commiſſion from you) may have power and Authority to ſee, that Divine Service be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted orderly and reverently throughout the Kingedome. So vvill our Biſhops and other Eccleſiaſticall Officers be the more carefull, that juſt cauſe of reproofe be not given, not juſt cauſe of your Princes and Magiſtrates proceeding againſt any, for diſorders and unſeemely perfourmance of Dutyes.</p>
                  <p>THeiſe Collections (moſt mighty and Dread Soveraigne) I have made out of ſacred Scripture, thereby in ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall perticulets to ſhew, how Gods Kinges and Princes in that antient Church under the Lawe, tooke care of, and by their Authority ordered, even Eccleſiaſticall things alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayninge to the Divine vvorſhip and ſervice. Hereupon I have adventured to note unto your Majeſtic, diverſe weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perticulers, wherein this our Church of Englande needeth the redreſs of your powerfull hande. If therefore you vouchſafe to be aſſiſtant unto the Church of God in theiſe things, you ſhall ſurely bynde the ſame unto you to hold your Memory bleſſed for ever: for, by orderinge theſe things, you ſhall both reſtore the Ordinances of God to his church, and diſpoſe rightly the extents of our Cleargy Iuriſdictions: you ſhall further the Preachinge of the Ghoſpel in all places of this Lande, and alſo be the Meanes, not of a pompous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice onely, but of a Stately, Magnificent, Holy, &amp; Proffitable vvorſhipp of God. Which beinge done, it will be no leſs
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150735:39"/>your Glory, that preventinge the abuſe of your and your Peoples Bounty by our Cleargy the Cleargy, have a large and rich Revenewe, togeather with Dignityes and Honors among your Nobles &amp; Gentry,</p>
                  <p>I neede not here prove from evidence of holy Scripture, that Kings and Princes under the Chriſtianity, are confirmed by God in the ſame Offices which the Kinges under the Lawe executed, this I ſhall prove elſew here, where I have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to write of this ſubiect to thoſe, who as yet are ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded of Papall leaſings, that they acknowledge not the ſame; but your Majeſtie profeſſinge your knowledge hereof, and practiſinge in your Kingedomes accordinge to ſuch know ledge, I neede but to certify of ſome things only, which even to this day neede redreſs in this our church of England. If it be obiected that I move unto Changes, &amp; that Changes are ever dangerous in Kingedomes, I then humbly pray your Majeſtie to conſider, that I move to no Changes but ſuch, as which the evidence of the will of God in Seripture witneſſeth unto. And what the Glory of Changes made under the Reformation, accordinge to the vvorde of the Lord in Scripture hath bene, the whole worlde now ſeeth, &amp; your Majeſtie enjoyeth and inheriteth the Glory and Power of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Doubtleſs, without a greate Change, and the ſame very ſtrange &amp; dangerous, we had had no Reformation of thinges; if therefore Gods vvorde hath made us happy in overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge the dangers of the greater Change, ſhould we neglect the yet further Conforminge of things to the vvorde, for feate of the danger of the leſſer Change? I beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie therefore, that you will ſo tender the Good of the Church of God, as that no feare of the danger of a Change, may hinder the yet further conforminge of things, to the evidence of the vvill of God as vve fynde it in holy Scripture.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150735:40"/>With which Petition I put an end to theiſe my Collections out of holy Scripture, humbly praying, that I may yet further continue this wryting of mync, ſhewing unto your Majeſtie the evidence of the prevaylinge, or not prevaylinge, of the Kingdome of heaven amonge your People, as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are good or bad, painefull or idle, who are allowed in this your Kingdome to poſſeſs our Spirituall livings. Verily, (my moſt gratious Soveraigne) who ſo loveth the prevay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge of the Kingedome of heaven, and deſireth the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Kingedome of Sathan, cannot but cheriſh and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice of the induſtrious Miniſters of the Ghoſpell, and be zealous againſt the negligent and idle Hopinge therefore of your Majeſties gratious diſpoſition towards the Kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, and zealous hatred of the Kingedome of Sathan, I vvill proceede to ſhew, the Meanes by which the Kingedome of Heaven prevayleth amonge your people, petitioninge alſo your gratious cheriſhinge, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>V. CHAP.</head>
                  <p>EXperience hath declared, that the Kingedome of Heaven hath increaſed, and Sathans Kingedome decreaſed, by the Ghoſpells beinge Miniſtred by Men, vvho have an inſeazo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Spirit of God; therefore every childe of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, as he loveth the prevaylinge of the one, &amp; declyninge of the other Kingedome, ſo he is to love, cheriſh and ſuſteine to his Power, ſuch Miniſters of the vvorde, as have cvidence of an inſeazoninge of the Spirit of God. The Seripture every vvhere vvitneſſeth, that the Miniſtration of the vvord through the Spirit in the Miniſter, is truly that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaylinge
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150735:40"/>vaylinge Power and effectuall Miniſtration, by which, if not onely, yet cheifely, the Kingedome of Heaven prevalleth, &amp; the contrary Kingedomes ſubdued; therefore though the vvorde Miniſtred by a wicked Miniſter may be of ſome, yet certainely it is not of like Power, as vvhen the Spirit of God aſſiſteth the Miniſter in miniſtringe the ſame. It is therefore none of the leaſt vertues of a godly King, to obſerve the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Ghoſpell, markinge in whoſe Miniſtration the Ghoſpell moſt prevaileth, and in vvhoſe not; the one to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh as proffitable Miniſters, the other to reprove as unprof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. Suffer me therefore (Dread Soveraigne) I humbly pray you, to ſet before your viewe in a breife manner, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſorts of Miniſters, which I fynde in this your Kingdome of ENGLANDE, and the diverſe effects in your people of their diverſe manner of executinge their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations; that ſo it may by the effects and Fruicts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pcare, vvho be thoſe Miniſters vvho cheifely have an evidence of an inſeazoninge of the SPIRIT of GOD.</p>
                  <p>Some are admitted Miniſters in the Church of Englande, vvho neither by the Spirit, nor yet of induſtrious Study cann Preach at all; therefore they content themſelvs to reade Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service onely, or at the moſt to reade ſome tymes a Homily to their Pariſhioners. Theiſe, vvhen they reade Divine Service, you ſhall fynde them to doe it very irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, poſtinge over it alſo as haſtily as they may: Alſo if they reade any Homilyes, it is then but ſeldome, and this alſo in ſuch a manner, as plainely ſhewes, that they little tender the peoples in ſtruction. If you obſerve the Speach or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of theiſe out of the Church, you ſhall fynde the ſame to be vvholy of the vvorid and vvordly things, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge no evidence of Religion, or of faith accordinge to the Ghoſpell.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150735:41"/>Yea, you ſhall fynde the moſt of theiſe to be pott compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and this alſo in the lewdeſt and moſt prophane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the Parriſh: they are as laſcivious as thoſe who have no feare of God; their talke alſo is full of fooliſh jeſtinges, if not alſo of ribaldry. Looke into the familyes of theiſe, and what ſhall you fynde? verily, as little ſhew of Godlineſs, feare of God, or faith, as in the moſt ignorant and prophane familyes of your Kingedome.</p>
                  <p>No Morninge or Eveninge Praier, ſcarce Grace before and after meate, little or no Readinge of the Scriptures, No repetition of Sermons, nor any Catechiſing throughout the yeare. As for your People in ſuch Pariſhes, you ſhall commonly fynde them ignorant in Divine Myſteries neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation: Careleſs to knowe them at all: Swearers, Drinkers, Ieſters, filthy ſpeakers, and in a vvord, vvithout any Showe of true Godlineſs, ſave onely that to ſatisfy the Lawe, they reſorte on ſundaies to the Readinge of Divine Service; but there, neither caringe to marke oughts for their inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor comminge away, to be oughts at all bettered in life or converſation.</p>
                  <p>In theiſe Pariſhes, you ſhall commonly fynde very few, if any, Bibles: no uſe made of them at home if there be any; Nor any religious Dutyes (as I ſaid above) exerciſed in their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, ſuch as are, Eveninge Praier, Grace before and after Meate, Repeatinge of Sermons, or Catechiſinge. Alas, what evidence of the Spirit of God in ſuch Paſtors? vvhat prevayling is here of the Kingdom of heaven? Doth not the Kingdome of Sathan rather prevaile in ſuch Pariſhes? verily (my Lord, and Kinge) you ſhall fynde under ſuch Paſtors as now I write of, the rudeſt, ignoranteſt, and wickedeſt of your people; therefore my humble petition is, that for the bette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of your people in ſuch places, and for removinge a ſcandall from our Church, ſuch unpreachinge Paſtors enjoy
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150735:41"/>not vvholy the livings, but rather be put to ſome ſmale ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and the reſidue beſtowed on ſome other who cann Preach the Ghoſpell. I grante that Homily-readinge is not wholy without uſe in ſuch Pariſhes; but yet no Divines but will confes, that ſkill in a Paſtor to divide the worde aright, as the Neceſſityes of the Pariſhioners requires, is much to be preferd unto the ſame: for though Homilyes conteyne excellent and ſounde Doctryne, and are fraught with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian precepts, yet they are ſo generall, that vvithout a ſkilfull makinge uſe of the perticulers in a Homily, applyinge things to the preſent Neceſſityes of the Pariſ hioners, they cannot proffit the people, as doth a ſkilfull Sermon compoſed by the Spirit in the Paſtor, and fitted to the occaſions of the tyme and of Perſons. For, in a Paſtor in ſeazoried with the Spirit of God, the Spirit aſſiſts in his choice, in his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and directs him ſecreately to the Doctrynes moſt prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the people of his Charge; therefore a Sermon ſo diſpoſed, is farr to be preferred before a Homily which is penned at random, ſervinge generally for all places, and all people a like. But when the people feele not their owne ignorance met with, nor their owne knowledge confirmd, nor their owne Manners reprovd or commended, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no Power in that read unto them out of a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. Neither are Homilyes written to occaſion in our Cleargy a Negligence of Study, but rather for the help of thoſe onely who cannot Preach ſoundly at all; therefore fart be it from our Church, to fetter a Congregation to a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily reader onely, if the tymes affoorde Miniſters who cann divide the vvorde of the Ghoſpell aright.</p>
                  <p>Thus having vvritten of one ſorte of Miniſters, I humbly pray, that I may proceede to another.</p>
                  <p>Other Miniſters there are, who though they cann, and doe Preach vvell, yet they preach as ſeldome as Lawe will permit
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150735:42"/>them. Herewithall many of them are looſe of life &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane in Converſation. Yea they are common pot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions: they ſerve as jeſters at great Mens tables: and make no conſcience of their Speach, ſo as they may gaine a Meales meate in ſuch company of Credit. In a vvorde, neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in their Converſation, nor commonly in their dealings with Men, they ſhew any Signes of a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious diſpoſition of mynde. If you examine their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, you ſhall fynde there as little exerciſe of religious Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, as in thoſe familyes where there is neither faith nor feare of God. In ſuch Pariſhes the voice of the people is, That they have a Parſon that cann doe well if he would: that he is a good fellowe, and the like; but they cannot commned him, either for any painefull Preachinge, or for any evidence of Piety And according to his evel diſpoſition and example, ſo you ſhall commonly fynde the Pariſhioners, to take all liberty in vvickedneſs, ſo farr fourth as they dare for the Law of your Kingedome. Here, what faith? vvhat Sanctification? vvhat feare of God? vvhat talke of religious thinges? here you may fynde ſome duſty Bibles in familyes, but they ſerve not for any uſe all the yeate longe, ſave onely to carry to Church on Sundaies. Here, ſcarce in any one family of the Parrriſh, you ſhall fynde, or Morninge, or Eveninge Prayer, the whole yeare thorowe: here, no Repetition of Sermons: no Catechiſing of the family at any tyme; yea ſcarcely Grace before or after meate. What evidence here then of the Kingedome of heaven? vvhat childe of that Kingedome would not mourne, to ſee here ſo ſmale fruicts of the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell? If it be obiected, that Morninge and Eveninge Praier, Readinge the Scriptures, Repeatinge of Sermons, and Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſinge of the family, are new taxes not laid upon Men by the Ghoſpell, then I anſwere, That theiſe dutyes are included either expreſsly, or by conſequence, in the Commandements
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150735:42"/>given us in the Ghoſpell. Moreover, becauſe thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly doe theiſe things, in whom the Ghoſpell moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayleth, therefore the not doing them ſervs as a Signe, that there the Ghoſpell prevailes not in people as it ought. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeinge every family is a Charge, where Parents have Charge of Children, and Maſters of Servants, therefore in every family there ought to be ſome Religious exerciſes, by which faith and devotion may be furthered.</p>
                  <p>Another ſorte of Miniſters there is, who both cann, and doe Preach vvell, yea and often, as every Sabbaoth day once; but though of the aboundance of their learninge, they leave excellent Sermons with their Pariſhioners, yet, what comes of it they care not, neither ever looke after its takinge any effect at all. And for all their Preachinge, yet obſerve them in their life and converſation, and you ſhal never heare them ſpeake of religious things, longer then they are in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit; for abroade, all the weeke and yeare after, their Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners fynde that their talke is wholy of worldly matters, ſo that by true Signes the Pariſhioners diſcover them to be wholy worldly mynded. Civilly courtious they are, but Men may eaſely ſee, that it ſprings but from Civility, not from Religion. Theiſe love their Pariſhioners, but it is but becauſe they reape Proffit by them; not for that they fynde the Ghoſpell and the Grace of God to prevaile in them. If you ſearch into the familyes even of theiſe, you may fynde commonly more ſtore of Bibles, and more uſe alſo made of them, then in the Miniſters howſes of whom I have before vvritten; but yet here you ſhall fynde the uſe to bee, onely as for a vvearinge out of the tyme with readinge, vvhich elſe they could not at preſent tell how to paſs away. Here you may fynde Graces before and after meate, &amp; gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally more civility in the family, &amp; more ſhowe of Religion alſo then in the former Miniſters howſes; but yet for Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150735:43"/>or Eveniuge Praier, Repetition of Sermons, or Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſinge, you ſhal hardly fynde theiſe things the whole yeare thorowe. As for the People in ſuch Pariſhes, you ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly fynde them better diſpoſed, then in the Pariſ hes whereof before I have written: they are commonly more Civill, and reſpective of their life and converſation They reſorte with more reverence to the Church, and have more ſtore of Bibles then in the Pariſhes before written of; but as for family exerciſes at home, ſuch as are Morninge or Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge Praier, Readinge the Scriptures at convenient tymes, Repeatinge of Sermons, or Catechiſinge, you ſhall not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly fynde theiſe things uſed throughout the yeare. If you ſearch them more narrowly, you may fynde indeed ſome good meaſure of knowledge of Divine Myſteries; but as for faith, or Sanctity through the Spirit: as for any converſinge of things of faith: as for any joy of things hoped for, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the Ghoſpell of Chriſte, you ſhall hardly fynde theiſe things in them, no nor Signes of them. Here we may thanke God, for the evidence of the prevaylinge of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven in this your Kingedome, and this by the ſight of a ſounde Divine Service, and Preaching, and peoples reſortinge to the Church; but we cannot here rejoyce of that Kingedomes prevaylinge, in the hearts, lives, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of your people.</p>
                  <p>I grante indeede (Dread Soveraigne) that it is no ſmale matter, that the Ghoſpell preſſed vvith your Royall Lawes, prevailes over Lords, and inferior Governours of familyes, ſo much as to bringe their familyes to the Church; neither indeede is it a ſmale Power, that hath brought even this to paſs. Moreover, if Lords, and other Governours of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, uſinge their familyes to the Church, doe leave them therewithall to God, hopinge that the vvorde preached, and Gods Grace accompanyinge the ſame, worketh in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150735:43"/>to make them inwardly good Chriſtians; not further uſing their family publickly, to Morning or Evening Praier daily, or to a reading of the Scripturs thorow, every one his or hir part, at convenient tymes, or to Repeating of Sermons, or to Catechiſinge, yet we may not doubt, but that in every ſuch family there is one, or ſome, in whom the worde of God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and faith in God groweth in them accordinge hereto, and ſo herethorowe there is in that family a private prayinge, and a private reading the Scriptures, and private Meditations, and ſelfe-Catechiſinges; therefore alſo vve may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne or reproach all ſuch families, as wherein publiquely, (the family gathered togeather) there is not uſually holy exerciſes perfourmed. But yet, becauſe the very Showe of Godlineſs is good, not onely for an evidence to Paſtors, of the prevailinge of Gods Grace in their Pariſhioners, but alſo for examples ſake to others, as ſervinge to provoake or incite one family by another in the uſe of ſuch pious exerciſes and Showe of Godlineſs, it is very behoovefull, that families have their publick holy exerciſes at convenient ſeazons. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede ſome of thoſe who moſt uſe theiſe pious family exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, make Religion a wearineſs to their family, by ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually drawinge them (in every minute of tyme, wherein they worke not) to theiſe exerciſes, that they leave no time for their familyes recreation and refreſhment, by ſportinge, dancinge, uſinge exerciſes of Activity, or exerciſes of danger for animatinge them to valiancy, and other like.</p>
                  <p>Thus by an extreame, a vice growes, and this both to the hurte of the family, and alſo to the ſcandall of the Ghoſpell of Chriſte; for ſome erroneouſly conceavinge, that Religion cannot ſtande with ſuch things, they make their Children &amp; ſervants dull, and ſlowe of motion, and unſit for the defence of the Kingedome and of the Church; and others thinkinge that the Ghoſpell admits not ſuch things, make the Ghoſpels
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150735:44"/>yoake heavier then the Lord would have it, and ſo make the people take offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therat. Yea, ſom have raiſed a reproach &amp; cauſed themſelvs to be a by-worde, through their puttinge the bridle of their owne worde in peoples mouths, reſtrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge them in thinges which Gods vvorde reſtreynes them not in: ſuch Men doe both themſelvs, and alſo the Ghoſpell wronge. The Scriptures declare the Lord not to diſlike, but rather to approve, of ſportinges, Gen. 26, 8, dancings, Exod. 15, 20, Iudges, 11, 34, 37, and of exerciſes of Activity, Iudges, 20, 16, 1. Chron. 12, 2; therefore none ought by a vvorde of their owne to reſtreyn Gods people in ſuch things. Such Men would make conſcience to doe as David did, who for the reſcue of a ſheepe, would followe after a Beare, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Lion, but this expoſinge a Mans ſelfe to ſuch dangers even upon ſuch cauſes, the Scripture rather approves then condemnes. Surely the Scripture commendinge as an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and Honor of Kingedomes, that there are Active, &amp; valiant Men in the ſame, 1. Chron. 12, 1, it doth conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently allow of ſuch hazardous exerciſes as incyte &amp; move Men to a valiant expoſinge themſelvs to dangers; therefore the baitinge of Bulls, of Beares, and huntinge of vvilde Beaſts and the like, are not to be condemned to be uſed by Gods people. If any evell be done, or evell Speach hearde in the uſinge of theiſe things, let that indeede be reproved and puniſhed; but let not Gods people be debarred from the uſe of theiſe lawfull things, under pretence that Religion and Holineſs will not ſtande with ſuch thinges. Would God that they that uſe theiſe things, would ſay, and reſolve, and profeſs, that ſeinge God is gratious to allowe them to ſporte, to dance, to uſe exerciſes for Activity, and even unto danger for animatinge of them to valiancy, therefore he ſhould not be diſhonored by any in the uſe of them; for ſurely if Gods people did this, the Lord would delight in his peoples exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150735:44"/>themſelvs in theiſe things. True it is, Mans corrupt nature is ſuch, as that hardly it cann uſe theiſe things without takinge Liberty with all, both to forget God, and alſo to put away his feare, in the tyme of their makinge uſe of theiſe things; but if Maſters of families, and publick Governours, as alſo their Paſtors, would teach them frequently to minde the Lord, and to have care in their hearts not to diſpleaſe him in their uſinge theiſe things, as alſo would be ready to reprove and puniſh any, that ſhould diſhonor God in the tyme of the uſe of theiſe things, then the corruption of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would be kept downe herein as in other things hereby: for the Awe of Goverment changeth the Manners, which a depraved Nature is apt to bringe fourth. And why ſhould not every one of every family thinke with themſelvs, that as to doe or ſay oughts in their ſportinges, one with another, or family with family, or neighbours vvith neighbours, vvhich vvould diſpleaſe their Maſters, and alſo their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats, knewe they thereof, were the next way to be deprived of theiſe Solaces and Refreſhments, ſo to diſpleaſe God, is likewiſe the next way to make him alſo to deprive them of them, and to plague the Land and them? Therefore people ſhould uſe theiſe things as by Gods permiſſion, havinge an Awe of God in their hearts, not to permit or doe any thinge in the uſe of them, which is truly a breach of any of Gods Commandements.</p>
                  <p>As for the Sabbaoth day, vvhereas ſome uſe exerciſes of violence unto Blood, ſuch as are baiting of bulls, or beares cudgell playinge, &amp; other like, theiſe, though they be lawfull at other tymes, yet not on the Sabbaoth; more harmeleſs ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces &amp; delights befits the ſame, both for conveniency, &amp; alſo for that it is a reſt, aſwell to Beaſts as to Men: the like I might ſay for hobby-horſes, and men in vvomens apparell (but this indeede unlawfull) vvhich our Maygaimes commonly uſe;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150735:45"/>for, even in indifferent things, there may be a fitneſs not to uſe them on the Lords Sabbaoth day. Theiſe things I thought good to touch at here, becauſe men are apt to erre by an erroneous reſtreinte, aſwell as by an erroneous liberty-takinge. Againe, I finde in thoſe who moſt uſe holy and religious dutyes, a cuſtome of long prayinge, as if they would make a cuſtome, or get a Name for great prayinge; whereas the Lord doth in Scripture declare himſelfe, to delight in ſhorte praiers, tendinge to the preſent occaſions of praying, vvhich alſo are fitteſt for the Spirits attendance thereto, and to be made in faith of that praied for. There is no truth in praier, when the Spirit, and faith, accompany not the things praied for; neither cann they conveniently accompany longe and tedions praiers. In Congregations indeede, there muſt be in the Paſtor a ſence of, and praier for publick offences &amp; Benefits, and the very rehearſing of many perticulers is there truly needefull; but in the private family, the occaſion of the prayinge, vvhither it be for the morninge or eveninge is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to be tendered, though ſom other perticulers for the common wealth may alſo breifely be remembred.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I noted ſome evells, whereinto ſome the moſt devoute, are apt to fall, that ſo ſuch evells may be prevented; but yet if this Care be taken againſt theiſe evells, it would be very proffitable that every family aparte uſe its ſelfe to ſuch Religious Dutyes. For, for vvant of accouſtominge a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily hereto, vve fynde that Men goinge to church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge from thence, make that all their Religion for all the vveeke after; never thinkinge any more of any thinge lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the Church, nor caringe to doe in the vveeke, as they vvere at Church taught to doe; vvhereas if at home the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily vvere uſed to theiſe pious exerciſes, it would occaſion a makinge conſcience to reſorte to Church, and there to vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp God vvith faith in the Spirit, aſwell as in the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150735:45"/>Geſtures of the Body: as alſo it would make them care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of that taught, to remember a parte, and ſome ſpeciall things, either to Beleeve them heartily, or to practiſe them in their Actions and Speach all the tyme of their life: for ſome things are to be Beleeved onely, other things are to be practiſed, and in both every hearer ought to be carefull, that he doe it as he is taught by the GHOSPELL of CHRISTE.</p>
                  <p>Thus havinge vvritten of ſome ſorts of Miniſters, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved unto your Majeſtie the effects of their defects in your People, I now humbly pray, that I may proceede to vvrite alſo of thoſe other Miniſters, in vvhom I cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, bleſſinge God alſo for them, and for the rich and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Fruicts, of their zealous and painefull Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Other Miniſters there are in this Church of Englande, who beinge learned, are alſo painefull Preachers of the word. They preach once at the leaſt, but ordinarily twice on the Sabbaoth day, if not once in the weeke dayes alſo. Theiſe obſerve their Pariſhioners, whither uſually in their life and converſation, they bringe fourth any Fruicts of their Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge. Theiſe vvatch over any erroneous opinions in their Pariſhioners, informinge them better, and ſtayinge their outſpreadinge. Theiſe watch alſo over the Manners of their Pariſhioners, aſwell their converſation as their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge, obſervinge vvhen they are either vitious or vertuous. Theiſe apply themſelvs to fit their Preaching alſo unto theiſe obſervations, uſinge Comminations or Conſolations as the peoples vices or vertues, neglect or obſervation of Doctryne gives occaſion. Which that they may the better doe, they obſerve &amp; marke the common fame that goes of any in the Parriſh, and herewithall they have their eyes and eares abroade in the Parriſh, even faithfull and godly Men, vvho
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150735:46"/>obſervinge the common converſation and dealings of their Neighbours, doe faithfully informe them how they fynde their Neighbours commonly diſpoſed: whither to obſerve religiouſly what is Taught them, or to neglect to obſerve the ſame. All this they doe, before any of their Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners come to ſuch height of iniquity, as to be publickly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, and proceeded againſt in any courte of luſtice: Yea and hereby they ſo prevent peoples ſo offendinge that well neere, rather they by their well directed Doctryne, and grave or Paſtorly Authority, then the feare of the Puniſhment which is by your Law to be inflicted, doe bridle and reſtreine your people from offendinge your Lawes. Theiſe, in their owne familyes, uſe Morninge and Eveninge Praier, Grace before and after Meate, Readinge the Scriptures thorowe in time, every one of the houſehold their turne or parte. Theiſe uſe their family to Repeatinge of Sermons, and alſo Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe them conveniently often. If you talke with theiſe, you ſhall fynde them religiouſly diſpoſed, affectinge alſo in all conference with Men, to leave ſome Seedes and gratious impreſſions, either confirminge Men in the faith of ſome ſpeciall thinge of the Ghoſpell, or dehortinge them from ſome wickedneſs to which they are (by reporte) inclyncable. Theiſe are religiouſly courteous, and affable, lovinge their Pariſhioners, not for their owne private gaine they have by them onely, nor onely for neighbourhood and freindſhipp, but, (after the example of the Apoſtles) for the evidence of their faith, and for the evidence of their receavinge carefully, and practiſinge conſcionably the worde of Life. Theiſe ſhew themſelvs by many apparant Signes, that they love and ſeeke the Salvation of their People, rejoycinge of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteable likelihood of many, and aſſurance of ſome, that they ſhall be partakers in the future Glorification. Theiſe are grave in geſture, ſober and meeke in converſation: they
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150735:46"/>are devoute: they are Holy: yea, a Man may by good Signes diſcerne, that from a Springe of faith in themſelvs they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte others unto faith, and from a ſence of the ſweeteneſs of obedience in themſelvs, they incourage or animate others to obey the Ghoſpell. In a worde, theiſe goe before their Pariſhioners in thoſe things, vvhereunto by their Preaching they exhorte them. This for the Miniſters themſelvs, and their familyes; now conſider the people alſo under them. You ſhall fynde here the common voice of the Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be to this effect: We have, (God be bleſſed) a learned and a good Man to our Teacher: he taketh greate paines to teach us: he loves us: he is ready to inſtruct and teach us, even in private conference, upon any ſcruple of conſcience: he is courteous even to the meaneſt of us, ſhewinge alſo by evident ſignes, that he heartily deſires the Salvation of our Soules. In theiſe Pariſhes you ſhall fynde in the people, in the meaneſt aſwell as in the greateſt, more knowledge in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Myſteries, then in the Pariſhes formerly written of. Here, more evidence of faith of thoſe holy Myſteries, and in God and in Chriſte accordinge to the direction of thoſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries.</p>
                  <p>Here you ſhall fynde more ſtore of Bibles in fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: more readinge in them: more proffit by readinge in them, then in the other Pariſhes. Here, eveninge, if not morninge and eveninge Praier: Here, grace before and after Meate, and the ſame done with Reverence alſo, and an evidence of faith, and feare of God. Here you ſhall fynde repeatinge of the Sermons at convenient tymes: Here, cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſinge alſo conveniently often. Here, the Neighbours will conferr ſome tymes one with another, aſwell of heavenly things as of vvordly: yea and this they vvill doe, not to ſhew what they cann ſay of ſuch things, or to get a Maſtery in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, but with a mutuall Hope for ſuch things, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150735:47"/>one another in the faith and eſteeme of ſuch things, animatinge one another to preferr them in their love and deſire, before theiſe vvorldly things, which all men have and enjoy. When I ſawe this in ſome, I rejoyced, as one who had founde ſome who are anſwerable to that exhortation of the Apoſtles, where he deſcribinge in ſome meaſure the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reſurrection of our Bodyes, 1. Thſſal. 4, 17, ſaith: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte your ſelvs one another vvith theiſe wordes. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs where people thus doe, as fit opportunity, and mutuall diſpoſition of myndes vvill ſerve, the Lord vvill drawe neere to heare their talke, openinge alſo their underſtandinges yet better, as we reade of him that he did, Luke, 24, 13.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, in theiſe Pariſhes vve fynde the People, not onely to reverence their Paſtor, but heartily to love him, beinge glad alſo to have occaſion of doinge any thinge, whereby they may manifeſt the Love they beare him. Here, there is an abſtayninge from uſuall and unlavvfull ſwearing. Here you ſhall not fynde uſually any exceſs in drinkinge, Here, no laſciviouſs, filthy, or beaſtly talke, no bold, luſtfull: and filthy geſtures; but rather you ſhall fynde here the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vertues, even an abſtinence from evell, and yet a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Love and delight as youth requires, but with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreinte of ſuch wicked exceſs. Here, in a worde, you ſhall fynde a comforteable ſhewe of Godlineſs: Here, a true evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Chriſtian life and converſation. Here therefore is indeede, an evidence of the inſeazoninge and habitation of the Spirit of God, both in Paſtor, and People: Here a plaine evidence, both of the Kingedome of Heaven in Power, and alſo of the weakeninge, if not caſtinge out of the contrary Kingedome, even the Kingedome of Satan. Of theiſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Pariſhes therefore I rejoice, and for your gratious favour towards them, for their better incouragement in well doing, I humbly petition your ſacred Majeſtie in this writing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:150735:47"/>But, ſome, and too many of theiſe, are in the number of thoſe, whoſe Miniſters are ſilenced, and whoſe people are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached with the nick name of Puritanes. My Lord and Kinge, I petition not that their errors be ſuffered; but this I petition, that the Miniſters leaving their errors, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alſo forſakinge them, both Miniſters and People may fynde you gratious towards them, by reſtoringe the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to their former Miniſtration, and by acceptinge the people as the Lights of our Lande for Religion. There is no Garden where vveedes will not growe; neither doe men deſtroy the Garden for the vveedes ſake, but rather vveede out the vveedes and preſerve the Garden ſtill. We may not conceave, that none that are true Chriſtians, and have the Spirit, fal into any errors; for Peter had his error, Galat. 2, 11: and the Churches of Corinth &amp; Galatia had their ſtrayinges from the truth, vvhen yet neither Peter was ſilenced, but onely the error he fell into withſtoode, nor thoſe Churches, forſaken, but onely the vveedes weeded out. And it is truly a harde thinge, that Mens Miniſteryes are wholy ſuppreſſed, for an error or two in Iudgement, whereas rather firſt, they ſhould be but ſtaied from Preachinge ſuch errors, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes upon obſtinate perſiſtinge, ſilenced. But ſeinge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our learned and painefull Divines, whoſe Miniſtry hath bene very proffitable in this Church of Englande, are wholy for ſome few errors ſilenced, I am now a petitioner, that their Miniſtery may be reſtored, ſo as they forſake thoſe things which truly are errors in them. And for the people, I humbly pray, that leaving to ſpeake againſt Lawfull Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and Offices in the Church, and againſt our Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, &amp; leaving to condemne Gods people in lawfull things, they may be relieved from thoſe ſcandales which vvicked Men caſt upon them. Surely (Dread Soveraigne) theiſe Congregations vvhere ſilenced Miniſters have bene, doe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150735:48"/>manifeſtly declare themſelvs to be Gods Saincts in your Kingdome; yea I have obſerved, that vvhere a Miniſter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Ordinances of our Church, hath ſucceeded in the place of a ſilenced Miniſter, Godlineſs hath more and more decayed in your People. I vvill not ſay it is the fault of their Conformity, God forbid; but this I ſay, it is the fault of their not exerciſinge like Paſtorall dutyes, as the ſilenced Miniſters exerciſed: and it is the fault of our Biſhops not preſſinge them to exerciſe ſuch, but rather leavinge them to a prejudiciall Liberty in Life and Converſation.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I, (my moſt gratious Soveraigne) adventured, to ſet before your viewe, the diverſe diſpoſitions of your People, according to the diverſely diſpoſed Miniſters ſet over them. I neede not now doubt of your Majeſties quick ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehention and diſcerninge, where in your Kingedome the Kingedome of Heaven moſt prevaileth, neither yet where are the beſt evidencyes of the Spirit of God. You have given ſuch Signes of your excellent judgement in theiſe things, that I rather rejoice thereof, then infourme you oughts at all.</p>
                  <p>True it is, that it is not rigour of Puniſhment, no nor Lawes, that vvill bring people on to theiſe holy exerciſes in their familyes, and to this bleſſed reſtreinte from ungodly converſation, ſo well as the vvorde of God frequently prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, &amp; wiſely directed, by a ſkilfull Miniſter Neither is there any expectation, that a vvhole People ſhould at an inſtant be brought to this meaſure of conformity to the Ghoſpell of Chriſte. Yet, if Pariſhionall Goverment, might accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany Pariſhionall miniſtration of the vvorde, the people would doubtleſs the ſooner be brought hereunto. Not that there ſhould be any violent diſgracinge, or proceedinge againſt all that preſently are not conformable, (for this were to provoake untymely the people, before the Lords tyme for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150735:48"/>their converſion be come) but that by little and little, with Meekeneſs and Gentleneſs, the Pariſhionall Governours drawe them on, to conforme themſelvs to the Rules of the Ghoſpell. But, where any family is too obſtinate, refuſinge for longe tyme to exerciſe therein any religious dutyes, there I humbly pray, that your Majeſtie incourage the Pariſhional Governours, to proceede on orderly againſt ſuch; for ſurely, a family that within its ſelf, doth wholy neglect all pions exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, is neere unto Atheiſme, yea though they obſerve cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarily their comminge to Church. This if your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie vouchſafe to doe, you ſhall ſurely make your Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall bleſſed for ever, even as is the memory of theiſe good Kinges bleſſed, of whom before I have vvritten. If it be obiected, that Tradition ſhews us no evidence, that ever at all the Church had ſuch a Goverment by Lay Elders alſo as which I now preſs, (for this is the difficulteſt Change I peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for) then I anſwere; If we receave the Office of Biſhops &amp; Arch-Biſhops, becauſe Tradition brings them to us, when yet we have not any great vvarrant from Scripture, both for Biſhops and Arch-Biſhopps, (though indeede for one, ſet over Teachers and Churches we have great evidence) ſhall we not much more receave a Goverment by Lay Elders, vvhich hath evidence as I have before ſhowen in Scriptures, yea though corrupted Tradition affoorde us no Light for ſuch? The Lord hath not given ſuch evidence to a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, which hath aymed at the pureſt Tradition onely, as to that which hath aymed to Reforme things by his vvorde in Scripture; therefore to Conforme the Offices and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Eccleſiaſticall, to that vvhich the Scripture gives us Light for, is ſurely moſt acceptable to God, and ſhall receave the greateſt bleſſinges. Therefore I vvill conclude this my vvrytinge, firſt vvith a petition to your Majeſtie, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittinge of ſuch a Pariſhionall Goverment, (having an eye
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150735:49"/>rather at the Ordinance of God, as we fynde it in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then at corrupted Tradition and its teſtimony and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority): and ſecondly with my Praier to God: That he give you a hearte to execute his will, and eſtabliſh your Throane in the Church, continuinge your flouriſhinge Kingedomes to your ſelfe, and your poſterity for ever. For truly, our Church prayeth well, where it ſaith: Almighty God, whoſe Kingedome is everlaſtinge, and power infinite, have mercy upon the whole Congregation, and ſo rule the hearte of thy choſen Servante, Iames, our Kinge and Governour, that he, (knowinge whoſe Miniſter he is) may above all things ſeeke thy honour and glory: And that we his Subiects, (duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deringe vvhoſe authority he hath) may faithfully ſerve, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; humbly obey him, in thee, and for thee, according to thy bleſſed vvorde and ordinance, through IESUS CHRISTE our Lord.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſties Loyall</hi> Subiect. THOMAS PROCTOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:150735:49"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in the Printinge.</head>
            <list>
               <item>IN the Tytle of the Booke, for conſormably, reade conformably.</item>
               <item>In the Petition to the Lords of the Parliament, page 3. line 1, for Ma<hi rend="sup">•tie</hi>, reade Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>. And lyne 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for off, reade of. And line 12. for off, reade of.</item>
               <item>In the Petition to the Kiuge, page 6, line 32, for ordeninge, reade orderinge.</item>
               <item>Page 7, line 9, for, your Royall Povverfull, reade, your Royall and Povverfull.</item>
               <item>Page 7. line 15, for, burnts Offeringes, reade, burnte Offeringee.</item>
               <item>Page 8, line 5, for, ovet, reade, over.</item>
               <item>Page 8, line 11, At conveyed, conceave that a full point ſhould be.</item>
               <item>Page 9, line 7, for not, reade, not. Line 31, for miply, reade, imply.</item>
               <item>Page 10, line 7, for, rhus, reade, thus.</item>
               <item>Page 11, line 6, for, frow, reade, from. Line 8, at labour, conceave, a, vvantinge. Page 12, line 28, for, I vvrite, reade, I vvrite of.</item>
               <item>Page 14. line 3, for, Preachers of the Ghoſpell are may, &amp;c: reade, Preachers of the Ghoſpell may, &amp;c:</item>
               <item>Page 14, line 6, for, vvho preach the Ghoſpell exempted, reade, Preach the Ghoſpell are exempted.</item>
               <item>Page 16, line 35, for Talks, reade, Talke.</item>
               <item>Page 17, line 29, at City, conceave a full pointe vvantinge: and in the ſame line, for, for, reade, For.</item>
               <item>Page 20, line 17, for, the Elders Church, reade, the Elders of the Church.</item>
               <item>Page 34, line 1, for, Scripturies, reade, ſcriptures: &amp; for, nſtruction, reade, inſtruction.</item>
               <item>Page 36, line 14, for, as ſuperfluous, reade, as are ſuperfluous.</item>
               <item>Page 38, line 21, for, Officet, reade, Oflicer.</item>
               <item>Page 39, line 28, for Iudas, reade, Iudah.</item>
               <item>Page 46, line 18, for Lands, reade Lande.</item>
               <item>Page 47, line 20, for, petion, reade, petition.</item>
               <item>Page 49, line 18, for, of, reade, off.</item>
               <item>Page 52, line 3, for and made, reade have made.</item>
               <item>Page 55, line 2, for but, reade both and line 5, for uuto, reade unto,</item>
               <item>Page 5, line 17, for alſo and, reade, and alſo.</item>
               <item>Page 60, line 2. for Offeringes, reade Offeringe.</item>
               <item>Page 63, line 3. for Childreu, reade Children.</item>
               <item>Page 67, line 7, for iu, reade in.</item>
               <item>Page 68. line 12, at idle, conceave a full pointe vvantinge.</item>
               <item>Page 69, line 3. for Kingedomes, reade Kingedome.</item>
               <item>Page 72, line 13, for commned, reade commend.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
